<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to Doctor Wallis, his discourse concerning the Christian Sabbath by Tho. Bampfield.</title>
            <author>Bampfield, Thomas, 1623?-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11692405</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11692405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30749)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 10:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to Doctor Wallis, his discourse concerning the Christian Sabbath by Tho. Bampfield.</title>
                  <author>Bampfield, Thomas, 1623?-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 80, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Fabian ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wallis, John, 1616-1703. --  Defense of the Christian Sabbath.</term>
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48219:1"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>There is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Printed a Book Intituled,</hi> A Treatiſe of the Holy Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity, <hi>in two Parts: The Firſt aſſerteth the Deity of Jeſus Chriſt and the Holy Spirit, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Eſſence with God the Father. The Second in Defence of the former, anſwereth the chiefeſt Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made againſt this Doctrine. By</hi> I. M.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> I. THe Caſe is briefly ſtated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> II. Sheweth that there is but one God, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and Former of all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> III. Aſſerteth a Plurality of Divine Subſiſtences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> IV. Of the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> V. Proveth the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 1. By his Names. 2. That God in the Old Teſtament in divers Places is Chriſt in the New. 3. By ſeven particular Texts of Holy Scriptures. 4. That Chriſt pre-exiſted his Incarnation in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, and is no Angel incarnate, but is Coeternal with the Father. 5. His Deity is proved by his Works. And 6. By Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip given to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> VI. Proveth the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt. 1. That he is a Divine Perſon. 2. His Deity is aſſerted from ſeveral Texts of Scripture. 3. By his Works. 4. By Divine Worſhip given to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> VII. Proveth the Unity of the Holy Trinity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> VIII. Containeth ſome Explications of the Holy Trinuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. 1. Of the Eſſential Being of God. 2. Of the Divine Perſons, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. 3. Of the Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Divine Nature and the Perſons, and ſome Shadows by way of Compariſon of the incomparable and inconceivable Being of God, and of the Union of Chriſt's two Natures.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>PART</hi> II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> I. Anſwereth Objections againſt the Scriptural Proofs of Chriſt's Deity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> II. Anſwers to Objections drawn from ſeveral Texts of Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> III. Anſwers to ſeveral Arguments againſt the Deity of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> IV. Anſwers to ſeveral Objections againſt the Scriptures, that prove the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> V. Anſwers to ſome Objections drawn from divers Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to diſprove the Deity of the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> VI. Anſwers to ſome Scriptures from whence our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries aſſert that the Father only is the true God. With a general Anſwer and Concluſion. Price bound one Shilling.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO <hi>Doctor Wallis,</hi> HIS DISCOURSE Concerning the Chriſtian SABBATH.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. BAMPFIELD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Fabian,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> near <hi>Bread-ſtreet</hi> End, 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48219:2"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO Dr. <hi>WALLIS</hi>'s DISCOURSE, Concerning the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Little after the Printing the Enquiry, Whether the Lord Jeſus Chriſt made the World, and be <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and gave the Moral Law? And whether the Fourth Command be Repealed or Altered? There was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed a Tract of Mr. <hi>Chafies,</hi> on the Fourth Command, I think, as Anſwer to that part of the Enquiry, which referred to the Fourth Command; and then another by one Mr. <hi>G. T.</hi> both which I had no ſooner Examined, but another was Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>John Wallis,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Which Diſcourſe of the Doctor's, as containing the ſtrength of what is ſaid for the Firſt Day, I hold my ſelf principally concerned to conſider.</p>
            <p>I find the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 1. would not on the account of the Day, whether the Seventh or the Firſt, give any Diſturbance to the Peace or Practice of the Church where he Lives, ſo that a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath be duly obſerved, tho' perhaps not upon what Day he ſhould chooſe.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48219:3"/>
            <p>What Day he would chooſe, I know not, but hope it would be the Day the Lord hath Choſen and Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>But the Queſtion is not, what Day he would chooſe to reſt upon, but what day we ought to chooſe, and I am willing to hope he would chooſe that Day, which after the beſt Judgment I can make upon his Book, I think, is the Seventh Day, and that he means that Day, by that, otherways Doubtful Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>And I think the Word is the Rule of Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And not the Practiſe of the Church where we live.</p>
            <p>Nor know I certainly what Church may be meant, for that he and I live in an Age, wherein there are variety differing a little from one another, nor am I willing to diſturb the true Peace of the Churches of Chriſt; but if in any thing they be defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in their Judgment, or Practice, their Peace lies in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to their Obedience, <hi>which is better than Sacrifice,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 22.</p>
            <p>And till the Lord bring that about, I ſee little likelyhood the Sabbath ſhould be duly obſerved, or have the full Bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on it, which is annexed to it.</p>
            <p>Nor do I think the true Sabbath is ſo hard to be found as he ſuppoſes, to whom I may ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Deut. 30. 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>This Commandment is not hid from thee, neither is it far off;</hi> 
               <q>'Tis not beyond the Seas that we ſhould need to go round the Earth to fetch it, (as the Dr. <hi>p.</hi> 79. pleaſantly advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) but the Word is very nigh unto thee, in thy Mouth, and in thine Heart, that thou mayſt do it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays alſo, p. 1. <hi>That he does not know whether</hi> Sunday <hi>be a first or ſecond, a third or a ſeventh Day, in a continual Circulation of Weeks from the Creation, or from Chriſt's time;</hi> and if ſo, he is at a great uncertainty, and I do not wonder if he be yet to chooſe his Day; which Expreſſions in his firſt Page, may give ſome Light to ſtate this Queſtion, for if he does not know from Chriſt's time, which Day of the Week <hi>Sunday,</hi> as he calls it, is, I ſee very little reaſon why he ſhould obſerve it.</p>
            <p>He adds, <hi>And what it is impoſſible for him to know, he thinks will be no Cirme to be ignorant of;</hi> and if he do not know what Day of the Week <hi>Sunday is,</hi> and much more if it be impoſſible for him to know it, I ſee no reaſon at all why he ſhould write a Book for the Obſervation of a Day impoſſible for him to know.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48219:3"/>
            <p>All the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> Churches in the World, I think, are agreed, that <hi>Sunday</hi> is the firſt Day of the Week, which Day I preſume by the reſt of his Book, the Doctor obſerves, and if we be right in that (as I think we are) that <hi>Sunday</hi> is the firſt Day, it will be no great Task by telling ſeven, to reſolve which is the ſeventh Day.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the impoſſibility for him to know what Day of the Week <hi>Sunday</hi> is, he is ſufficiently ſatisfied that we ought to keep a Sabbath, and ſo am I, and I think we may be ſufficiently certain, which is the ſeventh Day in the weekly Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, and am willing to obſerve that Bleſſed and Sanctified Day and Time, which I think is the Lord's Day, and not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and ſo not hard to be found.</p>
            <p>And I do not think God has left the ſtreſs of a Point, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Publick Worſhip doth ſomewhat depend, upon a thing impoſſible for us to know; by his Word and Works, he can make this plain to all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I agree with him, that the place of Worſhip under the Goſpel, <hi>p.</hi> 2. is not ſo material, whether this, or that, <hi>John 4. 21, 23. 1 Tim. 2. 8. God is a Spirit, and his true worſhippers did, do, and ſhall worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth.</hi> And I know no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour now for the Holineſs of Places, for which yet (as the Dr. <hi>p.</hi> 3.) ſome are zealous.</p>
            <p>I agree with him that <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> is of Human Inſtitution, which I think he admits by the words, <hi>ſo be it,</hi> p. 3. which I think does alſo lay aſide all other Holy Days, which are but of Human Inſtitution; and <hi>p.</hi> 13. about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> the Doctor ſays, <hi>It is not agreed amongst Chronologies, either what Year, or what Month, much leſs what day of that Month our Saviour was Born, yet</hi> (he ſays) <hi>we keep</hi> December the <hi>25th, in memory of his Birth, as ſuppoſing him to have been then Born:</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 45. he ſays, <hi>No Man at this Day knows what Day it was,</hi> and <hi>p. 13. That we are at ſo great uncertainty, as we reckon the Year 1692 from his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion to begin the first of</hi> January, <hi>and the ſame Year his Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not till the</hi> 25th <hi>of</hi> March <hi>after;</hi> as if his Birth and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion had been a quarter of a Year before his Conception: And ſo the Doctor leaves thoſe days, If I miſtake not, utterly uncertain.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 12. he tells us, <hi>The Paſcal Tables which ſhould direct us what day to keep</hi> Eaſter <hi>on, do put us further out then if we had none at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48219:4"/>
            <p>I agree with the Doctor, <hi>p.</hi> 2, &amp; 3. that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt according to his Divinity was God, and is ſo, the true God, the God that made Heaven and Earth, the God who delivered the Law at <hi>Mount Synai,</hi> and I think thoſe three, <hi>the father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, are on Jehovah,</hi> Deut. 6. 4. 5. <hi>Jehovah Aelohenu, Jehovah our Mightieſt, is Jehovah Aechad, is one Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, was, is, and will be one Jehovah,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>the Lord our God, is one Lord, and</hi> Mark 12. 29, 30. <hi>The Lord our God, is one Lord,</hi> which are the words of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And I agree alſo, that the Bleſſing and Sanctifying the ſeventh Day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. was by <hi>Jehovah, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit,</hi> which goes far in this Queſtion, and I think proves the ſeventh Day to be the Lord's Day.</p>
            <p>And when he has acknowledged the Father, Son, and the Holy Spirit to be three, yet but one God, the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> &amp;c. he adds, <hi>p. 3. But he cannot agree that Christ, as God, and Man,</hi> (in Contradiſtinction to the Father, and Holy Spirit) <hi>did all thoſe things, for he that is Chriſt, was not then Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Words of the Doctor, of what he does agree, and what he cannot agree, inſinuates, as if I had ſaid, that Chriſt as God-Man did all thoſe things, which the Doctor cannot agree, whereas he muſt needs know that is not ſo, for I neither ſay, nor ever thought (till that I read it in Mr. <hi>G. T.</hi> and the Doctor) that Chriſt was Incarnate at the making of the World, or at his giving of the Law on <hi>Sinai;</hi> ſo as the Doctor has not well ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized in this, and any Reader may ſee it is not ſo; for Chriſt took our Nature on him about 4000 years after the Creation; and I find not a word of any Contradiſtinction between the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Holy Spirit, and the Son in the Enquiry, but the direct contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> their oneneſs with the Son in thoſe Works, which they both cannot but know.</p>
            <p>And he adds, <hi>p.</hi> 3. what he ſhould rather ſay about our Lord Jeſus Chriſt's bleſſing the ſeventh Day, becauſe he was not then the Lord Chriſt, (God and Man) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeems to make the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize ſomewhat worſe, upon which he ſays, that I <hi>p.</hi> 64. lay great ſtreſs) for neither I, nor any other that I know, has ſaid or thought, that Chriſt, when he Bleſſed the ſeventh Day was then in the Fleſh, ſo that in this I think the Doctor blama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48219:4"/>
            <p>But the Doctor does acknowledge that the Son is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> (i. e.) that he is Lord; for which ſee <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 9. 10. &amp;c. and I think he does believe that the Son of God is Jeſus, that is, the Saviour, the only Saviour, and that he is Chriſt, that is, the anointed for that Glorious Bleſſed Work of Redemption, that is, the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> he is called, as I think, often in the Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Father has choſen us in him, before the foundation of the World,</hi> in him, that is, in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as Chriſt, is expreſly named, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 16. ſpeaking of Chriſt, <hi>as he by whom all things were created, that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth:</hi> v. 17. <hi>and he is before all things,</hi> he, that is, Chriſt, is expreſly <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 2, 3. there named the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who <hi>v. 19. created all things;</hi> and Chriſt is named our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in every Epiſtle from <hi>Rom.</hi> to the <hi>Heb.</hi> (for ſo far I ſearched a little) and that frequently, and ſometime after alſo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>G. T.</hi> (whom the Doctor in this Objection ſeems to follow) writes of this great Myſtery in two or three places under the like and greater miſtakes, and ſo at preſent I leave him. But for the Doctor to impoſe upon his Readers herein, as he does <hi>p.</hi> 2, 3. ſeems blameable.</p>
            <p>And why he thus begins in a Caſe which relates to the Deity of Chriſt with ſuch Inſinuations, for which he has no colour, that I know, from the Enquiry, wherein Chriſt's Deity and his being <hi>Jehovah</hi> is directly affirmed, unleſs it be at firſt to infuſe ſome Prejudice, I am not willing to conjecture.</p>
            <p>And as to this, if the Holy Spirit by <hi>Paul,</hi> names Chriſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>in whom the Father hath choſen his, before the foundation of the world, by whom all things were created, and who was before all things.</hi> I ſee no reaſon why Mr. <hi>G. T.</hi> and the Doctor ſhould vary from the Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and divers other Scriptures. And ſuch Artifices the Reader may diſcern afterward.</p>
            <p>I agree alſo with the Doctor, <hi>That God who made the world in ſix days, reſted the ſeventh day,</hi> Gen. 2. 2, 3. Exod. 20. 11. <hi>And that he bleſſed the ſabbath day, and hallowed</hi> (or San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified) <hi>it,</hi> Doctor <hi>p. 3. and here he does read it, not a ſeventh, bue the ſeventh Day;</hi> the ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> word here in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, &amp; 3. <hi>Hashebigni,</hi> which is uſed in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10, 11. which ſome would render there a ſeventh; and the Reaſon and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48219:5"/> Sence of <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, &amp; 3. does require, that it be rendered as the word ſignifies, the Seventh Day, for no man (that I know) does imagine that the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, &amp; 3. Bleſſed and Sanctified any other Day of the Week for Reſt, but that only, on which he Reſted, and that was expreſly not a, but the Seventh, and no other day of the Week; and ſo I think, for all after Seventh days in the Circulation of after Weeks, and Chriſt in the time of his Incarnation kept not a Sabbath, but the Sabbath, and ſurely he underſtood his own Inſtitution, and was not miſtaken in the Day.</p>
            <p>And the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 4. ſays, <hi>The Words he Bleſſed and Sanctified it,</hi> may be a ſtrong Intimation for Mankind ever after to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Seventh day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But (he ſays) <hi>is not expreſly ſaid:</hi> And that the Seventh day Bleſſed and Sanctified, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, &amp; 3. is not only a ſtrong Intimation, as the Doctor, but does in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Seventh day of every Week afterward in a continual Succeſſion, or Circulation of Days; and Weeks, I think, is proved by the Words of Bleſſing, and Sanctifying, or making Holy the Seventh day (which are comprehenſive Words) and from <hi>Exod. 20. 10, 11. as that day of every Week which Men were and are to remember to keep Holy.</hi> And God's Sabbatizing on the Seventh day, was, as I think, that Man might keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day in the continual Circulation of Weeks in a Spiritual Reſt.</p>
            <p>And in this Scripture <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2. we have the Foundation for the Seventh day Sabbath, where the Words are, <hi>And on the ſeventh day God had ended his work which he had made, and he reſted, or ſabbatized on the ſeventh day, from all his work which he had made,</hi> Heb. 4. 4. Where it is ſaid, he ſpake of the Seventh day in this wiſe, <hi>and God did reſt the ſeventh day from all his works and</hi> Elohim <hi>bleſſed the ſeventh day, and ſanctified it, becauſe that in it he had reſted from all his works which God created and made,</hi> Gen. 2. 3. And from God's Sabbatizing here, it is, <hi>That the ſeventh day is called the ſabbath,</hi> Exod. 20. 9. 11. And throughout the Old and New-Teſtament, from the <hi>Heb.</hi> root <hi>Shabath</hi> he kept Sabbath: And the Lords Bleſſing the Seventh day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. makes it a day of his diſtributing the greateſt heavenly Bleſſings upon all that obey his Voice,</p>
            <p>And his Sanctifying the Seventh day, ſhews it to be Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, and ſo ſeparated from all common Works, and earthly Employments, and ſhews it to be Dedicated and Sanctified by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48219:5"/> him, to his Worſhip, as an Holy day, and as his day (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the Lords day to be uſed in Holy Solemn Exerciſes of Religion as long as the World laſts, till Believers come to that Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm in Heaven, which remains for the People of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 4, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>And he that doubts the Seventh day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. does not include every Seventh day in the continual Succeſſion of Weeks, may ſee by comparing <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. that this Inſtitution is not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. as then firſt given, but as that which God had Inſtituted upon his creating the World, and the keeping the weekly Sabbath, was as abſolutely neceſſary for the Spiritual good of thoſe Believers, and others who lived in the firſt Ages of the World after the Fall (and of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> alſo if they had not fallen) as it is for us at this day, to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template his infinite Excellencies, and mighty Works.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 3. from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 11. he does agree, that God hath appointed (after ſix days of ordinary Labour) Man ſhould obſerve a Seventh day of Holy reſt, and this in a continual Succeſſion, which I think goes far to reſolve this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, not a, but the Seventh day only being firſt inſtituted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. and afterward obſerved as a Sabbath throughout the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>And if he agrees (as he does <hi>p.</hi> 3.) that it was the Seventh day that was Bleſſed and Sanctified, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. and that this is a clear and ancient Teſtimony for the Holineſs of time, as he doth, then, till another Sanctified Day of the Week, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weekly time can be found which is Bleſſed and Sanctified by the Lord; we are (for ought I can ſee) to reſt or keep Sabbath upon the Seventh day, as our Lord did, by whom we have no other weekly Day or Time Conſecrated, or obſerved as Holy, but only the Seventh day, and the Doctor's opinion of the Holineſs of this time has confirmed, and as I think eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed my Thoughts of the Holineſs of the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
            <p>I agree alſo with him, that the Law of the Sabbath is one of the Ten Commands, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and am not only willing to think (as the Doctor) but am ſatisfied it was a Law before, and that not only becauſe we find it obſerved <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. before the Law given at <hi>Sinai, Exod</hi> 20. (in which <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 25, 26. the Seventh day is called a Sabbath to the Lord, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the Lord's day) but eſpecially (as the Doctor acknowledges) for that <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48219:6"/> 2. 3. <hi>God bleſſed the ſeventh day, and ſanctified it,</hi> becauſe in it he reſted from all his Work, and I do, with the Doctor, think this a clear Teſtimony (and as ancient as the Creation) for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Time, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) as far as I can poſſibly diſcern, for the Holineſs of the weekly Seventh day, for there was no other weekly Day then, or ſince made Holy that we can find in the Word, but the Seventh day only) and this alone will go very far to reſolve and ſettle this queſtion.</p>
            <p>I agree alſo with the Doctor, that the Law of the Decalogue or Ten Commandments, tho' then given to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is binding to us alſo, <hi>p.</hi> 3. &amp; 4. And I think we have ſufficient Evidence from the Scriptures, that the Sabbath was obſerved from the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to the Flood, tho' he thinks in the ſhort Hiſtory <hi>Moſes</hi> gives of that time there be no mention made of ſuch Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Creation to the Flood.</p>
            <p>For <hi>First,</hi> on the Seventh day God (<hi>Heb. Elohim</hi>) had ended his Work which he had made, and he Sabbatized on the Seventh day from all his Work which he had made, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <p>The Example of God's keeping the firſt Seventh-day-Sabbath, is one undeniable Evidence of the Seventh-day-Sabbath kept after the Creation. For <hi>Gen. 2. 1. The heavens, and the earth, and all the Hoſts of them, were finiſhed before the ſeventh day,</hi> and ſo the Seventh day was kept after the Creation, and before the Flood.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Evidence is the ſame repeated, <hi>Gen. 2. 3. And God bleſſed the ſeventh day, and ſanctified it,</hi> becauſe that in it he had reſted from all his Work which he had Created and Made.</p>
            <p>Which Repetition of God's reſting the Seventh day, does ſtrongly inculcate and inforce our Duty, and certainly prove that God had reſted the Seventh day after the Creation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Flood.</p>
            <p>A third Evidence from the Caſe of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel, Gen. 4. 3. And in proceſs of time</hi> Cain <hi>brought an offering to the Lord,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 4. Abel <hi>alſo brought his offering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Proceſs of Time, <hi>Heb. Mikketz Jammin,</hi> at the end of Days, or at the cutting off of Days, <hi>Enquiry</hi> p. 23.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48219:6"/>
            <p>Which end, or cutting off of days, ſo far as God hath revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſeems to be the end of the Days of the Week, when the reckoning of Days was cut off, and after the Seventh day end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they were to begin to reckon again, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 'twas the Seventh day, the laſt day of the Week which before was Bleſſed and Sanctified, when the Creation upon the ſix days was finiſhed, which Seventh day was the end of the days of the Week.</p>
            <p>So as <hi>Cain</hi> (as bad as he was) and <hi>Abel,</hi> who obtained wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that he was righteous, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 4. both (as I think) kept the Sabbath, <hi>Cain</hi> outwardly, but <hi>Abel,</hi> no doubt, by that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Righteouſneſs, in an Holy, Spiritual, and Heavenly manner, <hi>to whoſe offering the Lord had reſpect,</hi> Gen. 4. 4. but to <hi>Cain</hi>'s offering he had not reſpect: And if the Seventh day then ended the Week, as it now does, and if none can tell us of any other end of days at that time, I may thence infer, theſe offerings were at leaſt very probably, if not certainly, upon the Seventh-day-Sabbath, and are a good Evidence for it.</p>
            <p>And the Righteouſneſs aſcribed to <hi>Abel, Heb.</hi> 11. 4. ſurely does import his Obedience to all Gods Wills then revealed, whereof the Seventh day was eminently one, and <hi>Abel</hi>'s ſacrificing the Firſtlings of his Flock was another, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
            <p>Which Offerings were Types of Chriſt, and proper for the Sabbath-day, which <hi>Abel</hi> offered unto God by Faith, and was a more excellent Sacrifice then <hi>Cain</hi>'s, by which <hi>Abel</hi> obtained witneſs that he was Righteous, God teſtifying of his Gifts, and by it, <hi>he being dead, and yet ſpeaketh,</hi> Heb. 11. 4. I think he yet ſpeaketh to us, to be Righteous as he was, and to obſerve the Seventh day.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Abel</hi> was a Perſon obedient unto God in all things; we have the Teſtimony of Chriſt, who calls him Righteous <hi>Abel, Matth.</hi> 23. 35.</p>
            <p>A fourth Evidence is from <hi>Gen. 5. 22. Enoch walked with God three hundred years.</hi> And ver. 24. <hi>and Enoch walked with God, and he was not, for God took him.</hi> Enquiry, <hi>p.</hi> 23. Which <hi>Enoch</hi> was a Prophet, and <hi>Jude</hi> 14. 15. Propheſied the Lords coming to execute Judgment upon all, and to convince all that were ungodly, <hi>Greek</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all Corrupt, or all no Worſhippers, thrice mentioned in the 15 ver.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48219:7"/>
            <p>'Tis true, thoſe who do not Worſhip God, or do not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him aright, are highly blameable; but the true Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Greek</hi> word being from Alpha privative, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to Worſhip: the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> does tell us who they were whom <hi>Enoch</hi> reproved, that is, ſuch as did not Worſhip God at all, or not according to his appointments, and does imply, that <hi>Enoch</hi> did Worſhip God aright, or elſe how could <hi>Enoch</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince others, if himſelf did not keep the Bleſſed and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Day; and whether the word in <hi>Jude</hi> 14. &amp; 15. do not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply alſo that the reſt of the then degenerated Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> whom <hi>Enoch</hi> reproved, did neglect the Bleſſed Day, ſeems as I conceive, very probable.</p>
            <p>And theſe are Evidences for the Seventh-day-Sabbath before the Flood.</p>
            <p>At preſent I paſs by <hi>Gen. 13. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 9, 10. Jaſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> becauſe by the Points, it may be from the verb <hi>Jaſhab,</hi> he dwelt.</p>
            <p>Evidences that after the Flood, the Sabbath was kept before the Law at <hi>Sinai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 2, 4. Enquiry <hi>p.</hi> 23. 24. the Lord appeares to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and promiſes, <hi>that in his ſeed all the nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed,</hi> ver. 5. <hi>Becauſe that</hi> Abraham <hi>obeyed my voice, and kept my charge, my commandments, my ſtatutes, and my laws.</hi> Bleſſing the Nations in his Seed, includes a promiſe of Chriſt upon <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Obedience.</p>
            <p>How <hi>Abraham</hi> came to know all the Commandments, Statutes, and Laws, I know not certainly.</p>
            <p>It may be, they being implanted in <hi>Adam,</hi> who was created in Gods own Image, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26, 27. were taught down along from <hi>Adam</hi> in gracious Families, from Father to Son, and ſo to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it may be alſo by ſpecial Revelation, but this is certain, that <hi>Abraham</hi> knew theſe, how elſe could he keep or obey them; and 'tis certain he obeyed the Lords voice, and kept his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and his Laws, and one eminent Voice and Law of God was, <hi>Gen. 2. 2, 3. and God bleſſed the ſeventh day, and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Abraham kept my Commandments,</hi> Gen. 26. 5. and in <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 16. 27, 28. how long refuſe ye to keep my commandments;</hi> the ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> word with that <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 5. and the Command which <hi>Iſrael</hi> brake, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 27, 28. Was that ſome of them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48219:7"/> upon the Seventh-day-Sabbath went out to gather <hi>Manna,</hi> which they ought not to have done; and ſo the Command which they brake, it ſeems was one of thoſe which <hi>Abraham</hi> kept.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Gen. 26. 5. Abraham kept my Laws;</hi> and in <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 4. The Lord to <hi>Moſes, I will rain bread from heaven for you, and the people ſhall go out and gather a certain rate every day, that I may prove them whether they will walk in my Law, or no;</hi> and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 27, 28. when ſome brake the Sabbath, and went out to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Manna</hi> on the ſeventh Day, the Lord ſays to <hi>Moſes, How long refuſe ye to keep my laws:</hi> it is the ſame Hebrew word with that <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 5. where the Lord ſays, <hi>Abraham</hi> kept his Laws; and the Doctor does neither offer nor pretend that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> brake the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Now if the Law broken by the <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 16. 4, 28. were the Seventh-day-Sabbath, as it certainly was, then 'tis very likely one of the Laws of God kept by <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 26. 5. tho the Sabbath be not particularly there named, was the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> brake, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. for we have the ſame Hebrew word for both, ſo that it does appear by <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 5. That <hi>Abraham obeyed the Lords voice, and kept his commandments, and his laws;</hi> and I ſee no good colour to doubt it.</p>
            <p>And he that ſays <hi>Abraham</hi> kept not the Sabbath, when God ſays <hi>Abraham</hi> kept his Commands and his Laws, may as well deny that <hi>Abraham</hi> kept any other of the Commands, or Laws of God; a Sixth is from <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 18. the Lord to <hi>Moſes, Say to the King of</hi> Egypt, <hi>the Lord God of the</hi> Hebrews <hi>hath met with us, and now let us go we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, three days journey into the Wilderneſs that we may ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lord our God,</hi> (which they could not freely do in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>) Exod. 8. 26.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Horeb</hi> (as Geographers obſerve) was, without hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, about three days Journey from <hi>Aegypt,</hi> concerning which Mountain, God foretold <hi>Moſes, Exod. 3. 12. When thou haſt brought forth the people out of</hi> Aegypt, <hi>ye ſhall ſerve God upon this mountain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon which Mountain the Law for the Sabbath was reinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 21, 23. The Lord to <hi>Moſes, ſay unto</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſrael <hi>is my Son, and I ſay unto thee, let my Son go that he may ſerve me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48219:8"/>
            <p>And <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 29, 30, 31. When <hi>Aaron</hi> had ſpoken to the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> all the words which the Lord had ſpoken to <hi>Moſes</hi> the people believed, and when they heard that the Lord had viſited the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that he had looked upon their Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then they bowed their Heads, and worſhipped; and it were not hard to ſay, 'tis probable that <hi>Aarons</hi> preaching to them all the words the Lord had ſpoken, and their worſhipping was upon the Sabbath day, as will further appear in <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 4, 5, 8, 14, 17, 19.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Exod. 5. 1. Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> went in and told <hi>Pharaoh, Thus ſaith the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>let my people go that they may hold a feast unto me in the wilderneſs;</hi> and 'tis not over hard to imagine what that Feaſt was, which by comparing <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. where the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> were drowned, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 1, 22, 23. where is <hi>Moſes</hi>'s ſong and the murmuring at <hi>Morah,</hi> and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 1, 23. its likely was the Feaſt of the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod. 5. 2. Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, <hi>Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey his voice, to let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go;</hi> and ver. 3. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſaid, <hi>the God of the</hi> Hebrews <hi>bath met with us, let us go, we pray thee, and ſacrifice unto the Lord our God;</hi> and ver. 4. the King ſaid unto them, <hi>Wherefore do ye</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron <hi>let the people</hi> (or make them to ceaſe) <hi>from their work, get you to your burdens;</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 5. 5. Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, <hi>behold the people of the land now are many, and you make them rest from their burdens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You make them reſt, <hi>Heb. Vehiſhbattem,</hi> which as I take it, is in the conjugation <hi>Hiphil, praeterit tenſe,</hi> ſecond Perſon, plural number, from the root <hi>Shabath,</hi> he kept Sabbath, and ſignifies, <hi>and yemake them to keep ſabbath from their burdens,</hi> the very ſame root in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2. God ſabatized, reſted, or kept Sabbath on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day from all his Work which he had made, and from the ſame root, <hi>Gen. 2. 3. and God bleſſed the ſeventh day and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it: becauſe that in it he had reſted from all his work, which God created and made.</hi> So as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> charges <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> as making the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to ceaſe from their Work, and as making of them to keep Sabbath from their Burdens.</p>
            <p>And when the Word of God is ſo plain, and full, and certain, and that by the Mouth of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> an enemy that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron</hi> did make the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ceaſe from their Work, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. and did make them keep Sabbath, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. For the Doctor to ſay againſt ſuch a plain Word (beſide what was ſaid before of <hi>Abel, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> &amp;c.) as he does <hi>p.</hi> 7. And I think ſometimes afterward to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48219:8"/> the like effect, that we have not the leaſt mention of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. 'till after <hi>Iſraels</hi> coming out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> may excuſe my ſo long inſiſting on theſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>So we have here in <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 5. expreſs mention of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ceaſing from their work, and keeping the Sabbath, and the Taskmaſters exacting their daily Tasks every day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 13, 14. ſhews this, which are evidences for keeping the Sabbath before they came out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Exod. 5. 17. Pharaoh</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids them as idle, therefore ye ſay, let us go to do Sacrifice to the Lord.</p>
            <p>And the Sacrifices, though they were to be offered every day, yet as a Feaſt-day, were offered on the Sabbath. And <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. 1, 8, 25, 26, 27, 28. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 1, 13. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. 3, 7, 8, 9, 11, 22, 24, 25. are agreeable to <hi>Exod. 3. &amp; 4. &amp;</hi> 5. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 12, 13. After the Plague upon the firſt Born, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> riſe up, get you forth, and go and ſerve the Lord, as ye have ſaid, alſo take your Flocks, and your Heards, as ye have ſaid, and be gone, and bleſs me alſo. And that excellent Hiſtory does ſhew, how the Lord delivered his people out of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s hand, and all his ſtrugling to hinder the Service of God, and to debar them of the liberty to offer Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Sacrifices unto him, did all contribute to make the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance more compleat, from that oppreſſing Bondage, ſedate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſerve God, and keep his Sabbaths, as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 23. where they had a Feaſt of Bread from Heaven. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. and I think <hi>ver.</hi> 13. of Quails alſo, beſides their Flocks and Heards, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>Another proof that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had the knowledge of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, and did obſerve it, and that before the Law at <hi>Sainai,</hi> is from <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>As to the Doctor's Opinion of a new Inſtitution of another Sabbath, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 23, 25. at <hi>Marah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that upon their murmuring there becauſe the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were bitter, which were there cured by a Tree which the Lord ſhewed <hi>Moſes,</hi> he made a Statute and an Ordinance, and there he proved them, <hi>ver. 25. &amp;</hi> 26. ſaid, <hi>If thou wilt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hearken to the voice of</hi> Jehovah <hi>thy God, and wilt do that which is right in his ſight, and wilt give ear to his commandments, and keep all his ſtatutes, I will put none of theſe diſeaſes upon thee which I have brought upon the</hi> Aegyptians, <hi>for I am the Lord that healeth thee;</hi> which ſeems expreſly the Statute and Ordinances before
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48219:9"/> mentioned, which Statute and Ordinance confirms the Lords Commandments, and all his Statutes, but alters none of them; ſo that the conceit of a new Sabbath day here inſtituted without any word from God, is a meer conjecture by learned Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> (as afterward) and what that Statute and Ordinance was, the Doctor ſays, <hi>p. 4. We cannot tell;</hi> which I think is enough to ſet aſide all new Epocha here. And <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 27. (from <hi>Marah) they came to</hi> Elim, <hi>where they encamped by other Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 1. They journyed from <hi>Elim</hi> to the Wilderneſs of Sin, and there they murmured again for want of Bread, and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 2, 3. the Lord to <hi>Moſes, I will rain bread from heaven for you, and the people ſhall go out, and gather a certain rate every day,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>And the ſixth day they ſhall prepare that which they bring in; and it ſhall be twice as much as they gather daily.</hi> ver. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And at even the quails came up,</hi> ver. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And every man gathered the Manna every morning,</hi> ver. 4. 21. which was every Day of the Week except the ſeventh Day, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>So the Lord there reckons the days, the ſixth Day and the ſeventh Day after the ſame manner as at the firſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>And this as it ſeems was not at <hi>Elim</hi> nor at <hi>Marah</hi> (but at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place and time) <hi>viz.</hi> in the Wilderneſs of Sin, which is between <hi>Elim</hi> and <hi>Synai,</hi> Exod. 16. 1. But that the Lord there altered the way of numbring the days, or inſtituted a new Sabbath day, no ſuch thing is there that I can find; but reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the ſixth and ſeventh days (which ſuppoſes the 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5, to make up the Week) in the ſame manner as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. to which ſeventh Day (as <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 5.) the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> were no ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>And the Sabbath, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. is here called the Holy Sabbath, that is, the Sabbath hallowed or ſanctified by the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. and the Sabbath is four times called the ſeventh Day, from <hi>ver.</hi> 26. to 30. But not a word of altering the Seventh-day-Sabbath as Mr. <hi>Chafie p.</hi> 31. nor any new Epocha, as the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 10. And ſo the ſeventh Day was not forgotten, but well known to them, and yet the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 10. tells us, <hi>That as to the ſabbath obſerved from the Creation to this firſt raining of Manna, that there is ſix to one that it is not the ſame, ſo that was uncertain alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48219:9"/>
            <p>Nor do I ſee any reaſon why a new Epocha from <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 23, 30. ſhould be imagined, unleſs it be, becauſe it is ſo plain a proof of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> obſerving the Seventh-day-Sabbath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law at <hi>Sinai,</hi> in obedience to the Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 23. which anſwers ſo much of learned Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s and of the Doctor's Books.</p>
            <p>And if there were no new Epocha in <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. then it ſeems agreed that the ſeventh Day was never altered till the coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And the fourth Command, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8, 11. I think puts this out of doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember the ſeventh day to keey it holy, ſix days ſhalt thou labour, but the ſeventh day is the ſabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> ver. 9. 10. that is, the ſeventh Day is the Lords Day, <hi>For in ſix days the Lord made heaven and earth, and reſted the ſeventh day, and bleſſed the ſabbath, and made it holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Does any fancy that the Sabbath-day here is meant A Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day? or that the ſeventh-day is meant only A ſeventh-day, and ſo that another Day of the Week is intended, and will anſwer the letter of the fourth Command as well as the ſeventh-day? I anſwer, (beſide what is ſaid in the Enquiry) That ſuch meaning of the fourth Command, I think is no where found in any Book before the time of Chriſt, nor during his Life, for ſuch a ſenſe would have gratified the <hi>Jews,</hi> to object againſt Chriſt, nor is it found whilſt any of the Apoſtles lived, nor I think in many hundreds of years after all their deaths.</p>
            <p>Does any doubt which is the Sabbath-day he is to remember to keep holy?</p>
            <p>Does any doubt which is the Sabbath-day which the Lord Bleſſed?</p>
            <p>Or, Does any doubt which is the Day of the Week the Lord made Holy?</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is here expreſs.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh-day is the Sabbath which the Lord bleſſed and made holy, which we are to remember to keep holy.</p>
            <p>Does any doubt whether the order of the Days of the Week, ſettled <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. was altered?</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48219:10"/>
            <p>The anſwer is here plain, <hi>For in ſix days the Lord made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and reſted the ſeventh day,</hi> which does refer to, and (ſeem to me) directly to confirm the days, and their names, of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. appointed in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. together with the time when they begin and end; and ſo I think we are thus far ſafe, that from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. to <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. there was no new Epocha of days, nor any manner of uncertainty, which was the ſeventh-day; there was no intermiſſion of the days by chance, nor the Day forgotten or neglected, as the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 61. nor as I think any manner of doubt when the days did begin and end.</p>
            <p>This ſeems to me ſo plain, as I had ſaid nothing thereof, if I had not found the Doctor inſiſt much, as if there had paſſed ſome alteration of days, and afterwards as if the Days began at Midnight, and as if I had nothing but Tradition, whereby to gueſs which is the ſeventh-day from the Creation, to <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. for which we have before ſo many highly probable, and other certain Scripture Proofs, and for which the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand alone is proof enough, being declarative of what was bleſſed and hallowed before in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. and is here in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. explained and confirmed.</p>
            <p>The Oracles of God were committed to the <hi>Iſraelites, Rom.</hi> 3. 2. to them was committed the keeping the Old Teſtment, and therein the Moral Law, and therein the fourth Command, and therein the ſeventh-day, and the Laws given at <hi>Sinai,</hi> are ſaid to be true Laws, and good Commandments (and ſo they certainly were and are both true and good) and the Lord made known unto them his holy Sabbaths, <hi>Nehe.</hi> 9. 13, 15. and if they were made known to them, then they knew his holy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and if they knew them, as they did, then his Sabbaths were not altered.</p>
            <p>And whether other Nations did meaſure their time by Weeks <hi>p.</hi> 5. See Mr. <hi>Chafie,</hi> chap. 13. p. 45. chap. 14. p. 49. I think expreſly for it.</p>
            <p>And to argue from <hi>Abel, Enoch, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> with ſuch high Characters as the Lord gives them in his word, and of <hi>Abraham</hi> as keeping his Laws and his Commandments, are as I think ſtrong arguments to prove the matter of fact, and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expreſſed that they kept the Sabbath, which is one of the Commandments, tho the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 7. thinks them weak.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48219:10"/>
            <p>And from their Practice, and the Scriptures before cited, I think we have a certainty thereof, whereof the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 8. ſays, <hi>We have ſcarce a Conjecture, which ſeem hard Words against one, and yet harder against ſo many Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' I am willing to thank the Doctor for what he would give me to begin the Week on <hi>Monday, p.</hi> 9. (that ſo his <hi>Sunday</hi> may be the Seventh-day) yet I do not think any Mans Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo great as to alter the way of numbring the Days which God hath ſettled, or to controul, or alter the Day God has Bleſſed, and I am content with Gods Allowance and Command therein.</p>
            <p>What is offered about the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> and <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and <hi>Circumciſion, p.</hi> 11. being ſometimes intermitted, I think does confirm the Seventh-day, and not hurt it, for that when the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> returned to thoſe appointments they kept them again.</p>
            <p>And if it be true (which <hi>p.</hi> 13. the Doctor thinks without doubt, and certain) that we do not know which is the Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, in a continual Circulation from the Creation, then all the Doctors Arguments before and afterwards for the Firſt day, are here as it ſeems without doubt, and certainly anſwered by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for if we do not know which is the Seventh day, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know which is the Firſt day, and ſo cannot poſſibly keep a Day which we know not; and ſomewhat like this he offers <hi>p.</hi> 1. Nor do I ſee how the Doctor or any other Perſon can be long held to think as they ſeem to do.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 1. He thinks it impoſſible for him to know the Firſt day, and <hi>p.</hi> 14. Impoſſible for any Man to know the Seventh day, which are alſo directly againſt him.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 16. he ſays, <hi>We have no particular Command in another Caſe,</hi> which I think we have, and not only a practice, moſt likely to be Gods Will, <hi>p.</hi> 17. But that not being now in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I paſs it by.</p>
            <p>And as to what he there ſays for the change of the Seventh to the Firſt day, that I would think ſo alſo if I were not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe prepoſſed with Prejudice, and with a great fondneſs to find out ſomewhat wherewith to find fault.</p>
            <p>I Reply, that I doubt we have many great Faults not hard to be found, and I commend to the Doctor <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17. But I know nothing of Prejudice or Fondneſs, corrupt Nature and human Frailties, by Grace diſallowed in this, and all Caſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as he ſurmiſes; but whenſoever I find in the Scriptures
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48219:11"/> any Truth which would correct my Converſation, and make it agreeable to Gods Will, after due ſeach and conſideration ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and conſcientiouſly to comply with it, as other Chriſtians do or ought; and this queſtion has been conſidered by me now near twenty ſix Years.</p>
            <p>And if ſuch Truth, according to the beſt of that Knowledge God hath graciouſly given concern others alſo, then to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it, and if it be a Truth, which can be by me no other way opened to them, then to do it in this ſort, as I weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can, and I ſhall be heartily glad the Doctor or any other would do it much better, as he is very well able.</p>
            <p>And if we are not to hide our ſelves from our Brother's Ox, or his Sheep when we ſee them go aſtray, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>And if we are obliged when others, eſpecially our Brethren, err in Judgment or Practice to reprove them, How much more are we bound when we ſee many erring in a moral Duty, to endeavour to ſet them right?</p>
            <p>And to ſurmiſe upon him that he writes thoſe Reflections, and many others, to prepoſſeſs and prejudice Readers I am loath to do.</p>
            <p>Nor had I made this Vindication if I had not been compelled by the Doctor's Charge.</p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> keeping the true Seventh-day-Sabbath commanded <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. from thence to the Incarnation of our Lord, I do not remember the Doctor to deny it; for which I think there is enough ſaid in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 26. 27, 28. and much more might be added if need were; and I am unwilling to write again the ſame things, altho' by repeating the ſame Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and reinforcing the old with new Words; I am ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time conſtrained ſo to do.</p>
            <p>And in general I ſay, that as far as I can judge, there is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſaid in the Enquiry to prove that (not A, but) The Sabbath Inſtituted <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. and Repeated <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and obſerved from thence to Chriſts coming, and (with every tittle of the reſt of the Moral Law) confirmed, and made perpetual by Chriſt in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 17, 18, 19. and <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 14, 17. who cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knew the true Sabbath day, binds all men, till the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth paſs away, which is not yet.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48219:11"/>
            <p>And (not A Seventh day, but) The Seventh day there eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and made perpetual, was obſerved by Chriſt, during his Life, for ſo was his cuſtom, <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 16, to 21. <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 38. 39, 41, 42, 43, 45. and was obſerved by Believers after his Death, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion; ſo was <hi>Paul</hi>'s cuſtom, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2. which was never altered by the Word that I know.</p>
            <p>Which confirming and making the Law perpetual, and every Jot and Tittle of it by Chriſt, who was and is Jehovah, does alſo fully prove (as I think) that (not A, but) the Seventh-day-Sabbath was neither altered, nor changed, nor forgotten, nor any way uncertain to Chriſts time, neither as to the day, nor as to the beginning or ending of it, and that the Seventh day is the Lords Day.</p>
            <p>This being premiſed, let us conſider what the Doctor further offers for the Firſt, or againſt the Seventh day; <hi>p.</hi> 17. 18. he tells us, <hi>That Chriſt on the day of his reſurrection, did not only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the good Women at the Sepulchre, and declare to them the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, but alſo the ſame day himſelf declares it to two of them going to</hi> Emmaus, Luke 24. 27, 32. <hi>and did expound to them in all the Scriptures, the things concerning himſelf, and did open to them the the Scriptures, and did</hi> (as he takes it) <hi>celebrate the Lords Supper,</hi> implyed in the words, <hi>he took bread, and bleſſed it, and brake, and gave to them,</hi> ver. 30, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Chriſt after the Reſurrection, appeared to <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and to the other <hi>Mary, Matth.</hi> 28. 1. 9.</p>
            <p>And the Angel ſaid to them, <hi>v.</hi> 5. and <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 5, 6. <hi>He is not here but is riſen, go tell his diſciplees that he is riſen from the dead, which they did, but the Diſciples believed them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now 'tis certain, as 'tis agreed, that Chriſt roſe the Third day, which Third day was the Firſt day of the Week; and that the Angel <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 5. (and two Angels <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 4. and <hi>John</hi> 20. &amp; 12.) ſaid to the Women, <hi>that Christ was riſen, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men told it to the Diſciples, yet the Diſciples would not believe them;</hi> and we have Chriſt appearing to two Diſciples as they travelled into the Country, <hi>Mark. 16. 12. And they went and told it to the reſt of the Diſciples, but they believed not them,</hi> Verſe the 13.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt's appearing to the Women, was a practical proving of the Reſurrection.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48219:12"/>
            <p>Some think the two Diſciples, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 12. to be the two Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples traveling to <hi>Emmaus, Luke</hi> 24. 13. which is very likely, and that <hi>Peter</hi> from <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 34. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 5. was one of them. But 'tis certain they were two Diſciples, and yet the reſt would not believe them, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 13.</p>
            <p>And their Diſcourſe upon the way as they travelled together, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 13. was ſuch as the Doctor mentions, and Chriſt there reproved them for not believing what the Prophets had ſpoken, <hi>v.</hi> 25. That Chriſt ought to ſuffer, but did not reprove them that we read, for travelling on that day.</p>
            <p>And 'tis likely the Breaking and Bleſſing of Bread, <hi>ver.</hi> 30. might be (for ought I know) the Sacrament of the Supper, and implied.</p>
            <p>But ſtill the Journey from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> and back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain was a travelling Journey, being near fifteen Miles, and more then a Sabbath days Journey, as the Doctor agrees; and I do not ſee how he can make that Journey conſiſt with the keeping that Firſt day as a Sabbath, whereof there is there, or before no Inſtitution, nor any Mention, but rather the direct contrary; their travelling upon that Firſt day of the Week (without any reproof from Chriſt) as upon any other of the Six days, ſeems directly againſt the Doctor.</p>
            <p>And whether our Lord did then travel without pain (as the Dr.) is not written; he had then the Wounds in his Body, and at his appearing afterward to the Diſciples, and <hi>Thomas, John 20. 25, 27. Luke</hi> 24. 29. and yet might be without pain, for ought I know, but ſurely the two Diſciples travelled as others do.</p>
            <p>And although the Diſciples were eminently Holy, yet becauſe not written, I do not know what they were then imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (unleſs it were mourning and weeping, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 10.) (where they were aſſembled for fear of the Jews, <hi>John</hi> 20. 19.) before or after the report of the Women, whom they did not credit.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 19. I think the Doctor agrees the meeting of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples there providential, and not upon a Sabbath account, for 'twas for fear of the Jews.</p>
            <p>And Chriſts appearing to the Eleven as they ſat at Meat, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 14. agrees therewith, it was as they ſat at Meat.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48219:12"/>
            <p>And to what he offers <hi>p.</hi> 19. from <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 36. &amp; 42. and <hi>John</hi> 20. 19. our Lords appearing to the Diſciples at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>peace be unto you.</hi> So <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 14, 15, 16. I anſwer, this Salutation of Peace be unto you, or ſuch like, is frequent in the Scriptures, and muſt be ſtrangely and ſtrongly forced to ſpeak any thing of inſtituting the Firſt day.</p>
            <p>The Reſurrection was and is a great Truth, and neceſſary to be known and aſſured, and yet the Diſciples were unbelieving of it, notwithſtanding all that Chriſt told them before his Death, <hi>Mark 9. 31. That he ſhould be delivered into the hands of Men, and be killed, and after that riſe the third day,</hi> as <hi>Mark 10. 33, 34. Luke</hi> 24. 7, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And his Reſurrection was proved to them by ſeveral Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 10. whoſe words ſeemed to them as Idle tales, <hi>v.</hi> 11. and the Lord himſelf upbraides them for their hardneſs of heart, becauſe they believed not them who had ſeen him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was riſen, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 14. So it became neceſſary (if I may ſo ſay) for the Lord to give full and undeniable Evidence of the Truth of his Reſurrection, by his Perſonal appearing to the Eleven upon the very day thereof, as he did, as they ſat at Meat, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 14. that there might be no room left for any doubt of his being actually riſen from the Dead. A Truth upon which the whole Doctrine of the Goſpel did, and does eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depend; and this I think is a fair account of our Lords appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Diſciples at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that this did alter the Seventh, or appoint the Firſt day for a Sabbath, I find not, but ſeems all dark Conjecture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any warrant from the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And yet the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 20. ſays, <hi>all which being put together, ſeems to him very like the Celebration (if not the Conſecration) of a Chriſtian Sabbath, or day of Holy Reſt, and Religious Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fully acknowledge, that all that was ſpoken by our Lord, as well before as after his Reſurrection, was Spiritual and Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon all the Sabbaths he kept as his Cuſtom was, and at all other times before and after his Reſurrection, but yet, that that which the Doctor allows, as it ſeems to me, as providential, and not upon a Sabbatical account ſhould alter the Seventh day, or inſtitute the Firſt, I ſee not.</p>
            <p>And we do not read the Lord blaming his Diſciples for reſting upon the Sabbath day, or for travelling upon the Firſt, but for their not believing his Reſurrection.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48219:13"/>
            <p>So as the Seventh-day-Sabbath (by all the Doctor has yet offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) ſeems not hurt.</p>
            <p>From <hi>John 20. 26. After eight days Chriſt appeared to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and</hi> Thomas <hi>with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt had appeared to the Eleven Diſciples at Evening upon the day of his Reſurrection, as they ſat at Meat, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 14. which was the Firſt day of the Week, <hi>John</hi> 20. 19. when they were aſſembled for fear of the Jews, but <hi>Thomas</hi> not being there <hi>John 20. 24. would not believe, unleſs he ſhould thrust his hand into his ſide,</hi> ver. 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And after eight days, Chriſt appeared to the diſciples, and</hi> Thomas <hi>with them,</hi> John 20. 26. and ſaith to <hi>Thomas, reach hither thy hand, and thriſt it into my ſide, and be not faithleſs, but believing,</hi> ver. 27. which was an admirable Condeſcenſion of our Lord to cure his, and all others unbelief.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Words after eight Days, the Doctor thinks was that day ſeven-night, <hi>&amp;c. The Cavil,</hi> for ſo the Doctor calls it, he ſays, <hi>is ſo weak, that he is ſorry to ſee it,</hi> p. 20. And then takes great pains to prove, <hi>That after eight days</hi> (as we commonly ſpeak in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> on that day ſeven-night) <hi>is the next First day after the Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have peruſed the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 50. 51. that after eight days is not that day ſeven-night. and I neither diſcern it to be a Cavil, nor ſo weak as the Doctor repreſents it; but that after eight days may be, as it ſeems to me, the ſecond or third day ſeven-night after the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Matth. 26. 2, 6, 14, 16, 17. after two days was the paſſover,</hi> ſeems to be meant, <hi>after two days excluſively,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>excluding the day on which that was ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. 11. 11. <hi>After three days and an half, about the two witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the ſpirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet,</hi> is underſtood as I think, with Reaſon, after not two, but three Days, or Years, and an half expired, God will revive them, and reſtore them to his Service, and 'tis ſame Greek word for, after, here, as <hi>John</hi> 20. 26. So after eight days, may not include the day wherein 'twas ſpoken, and ſo may be the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third day ſeven-night after.</p>
            <p>And I do not know that ever I heard, much leſs do we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo ſpeak, that after eight days is that day ſeven-night af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or that after eight days, does include the day wherein it is ſo ſaid for one of the eighth days, and if it did include it,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48219:13"/> yet after eighth ſeems to be the ninth, and that in <hi>John</hi> 20. 26. was alſo ſpoken in the Evening, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) near the end of that day.</p>
            <p>As for what the Doctor offers, that after eight days muſt be that day ſeven night, becauſe Chriſts riſing the third day, is ſaid in <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 31. to be after three days.</p>
            <p>I ſay the Crucifixion was upon the ſixth day, the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the firſt Day of the next Week, which does explain what is meant by after three days, <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 31. that is, after part of the Sixth day, the whole ſeventh Day, and part of the Firſt day.</p>
            <p>Now, when after three days, is ſo explained in divers Scriptures to be the third day, it may not follow, that after eight Days, which is no where that I know, ſo explained, muſt include the Day ſpoken in, and exclude the day after the Eighth.</p>
            <p>And that the Reſurrection was upon the third day, I think there is enough offered in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> ſee <hi>Matth, 6. 21, &amp; 17. 23, &amp; 20. 19, &amp; 27. 64. Mark 9. 31. &amp; 10. 34. The words of our Lord, The Son of Man ſhall riſe again the third day, Luke 9. 22, &amp; 13. 32, &amp; 18. 33, &amp; 24. 7, &amp; 21. 46. 1 Cor. 15. 4. He roſe again the third day,</hi> ſo as the Reſurrection was on the third Day, and the words, after three Days, are fully explained to be the third Day, or in, on, or upon the third Day, and the firſt of theſe three Days is expreſly included.</p>
            <p>And <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after, ſometimes ſignifies, in, and <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 31. ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in three Days, anſwers that Objection, and the Enemies <hi>Matth.</hi> 27. 64. deſired <hi>Pilate</hi> that the Sepulchre might be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red untill the third Day, that is, till the third Day is come, not till after the third Day is paſt, and ſo the Enemies underſtood the Reſurrection would be in or on the third Day, and all Scholars know that.</p>
            <p>Greek Prepoſitions and Particles, are often variouſly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as the reaſon of the place where they are uſed does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>And if this place in <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 31. be ſo rendered in three Days, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) after the third Day is come, that agrees with all the above cited Scriptures, for his riſing the third Day, and ſo <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> and other Annotators on <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 31.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48219:14"/>
            <p>And there is this difference as before, that after eight days is no where explained to be the eighth day, including the firſt of the eight, or excluding the day after the eighth, nor explained by, in eight days, as after three days, in <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 31. is expreſly explained by many Scriptures to be the third day, (and as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove in three days (<hi>i. e.</hi>) till the third day).</p>
            <p>What is offered <hi>p.</hi> 22. from <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 59. on the eighth day they came to Circumciſe <hi>John,</hi> was according to the Inſtitution, <hi>Gen. 17. 12. He that is eight days old ſhall be circumciſed,</hi> which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution does actually include the day of Birth, for that the day of Birth is one day, and ſeven days more do accompliſh eight days, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 21. but 'tis no where ſaid of that (that I know) that 'twas after eight days that they were to be Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>But if after eight days did include the firſt of the eight days, and did exclude the day after the eighth day, yet here is no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogating the Seventh-day-Sabbath, nor any inſtituting the firſt day, not any word to any ſuch purpoſe; but this ſeems an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion taken by our Lord (after eight days after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) when <hi>Thomas</hi> was with the reſt of the Diſciples who was not preſent at Chriſts firſt appearing to them, to cure his unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and to confirm the Faith of the reſt of the Diſciples, and of all others, in theſe two great Doctrines, one of the Deity of Chriſt, whom <hi>Thomas</hi> there openly and expreſly owns to be the Lord his God, <hi>My Lord, and my God,</hi> John 20. 28, 29.</p>
            <p>The other of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, which till then <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid, <hi>he would not believe,</hi> John 20. 24, 25. In which two great Doctrines the reſt of the Diſciples were before confirmed, as in the <hi>Enquiry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>p.</hi> 23. to <hi>p.</hi> 28. the Doctor would make the day begin at mid-night, and to end at mid-night, according to the Roman account, and that to be the Evening and the Morning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. and from mid-night to mid-night to be the day.</p>
            <p>And though I am not willing to contend about terms, what is the Natural, and what the Artificial day, yet I may not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Days of the Week to be any other than what God firſt fixed in the Scriptures, that is the Evening, and the Morning. 'Tis true, the Day as diſtinguiſhed from the Night begins in the Morning, and ends in the Evening; and the Night, or Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as diſtinguiſhed from Day, begins in the Evening, and ends
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48219:14"/> in the Morning, but the whole day conſiſted of Evening and Morning, that is, of Night and Day; and we find <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 3. that when Light was Created, <hi>Let there be light.</hi> Ver. 4. <hi>God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the light from the darkneſs.</hi> Ver. 5. <hi>And God called the light Day, and the darkneſs he called Night: and the evening and the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were the first day:</hi> And ſo the Light was the Day, and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Night, as diſtinguiſhed from one another; but one Day, or the Firſt Day of the Week, conſiſted of Evening and Morning, that is, of Darkneſs and Light, which was the Firſt day. And ſo <hi>Ver. 8. the evening and the morning were the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day;</hi> and <hi>ver. 13. the evening and the morning were the third Day;</hi> and <hi>ver. 19. the evening and the morning were the fourth Day;</hi> and <hi>ver. 23. the evening and the morning were the fifth Day;</hi> and <hi>ver. 31. the evening and the morning were the ſixth Day; and the ſeventh day God reſted,</hi> or Sabbatized, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. where Seventh day is thrice mentioned, <hi>And God bleſſed the ſeventh day, and ſanctified it,</hi> or made it Holy: which making it Holy, I think, reſolves the main Queſtion, which Days of the Week, conſiſting of Evening and Morning, that is, of Darkneſs and Light, and ſo beginning in the Evening, and ending the Evening after, is there appointed and fixed, and material and plain, and may not be altered. And our manner of reckoning of days here, I think is not in queſtion now between us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 22. He takes notice about what time, <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> came to the <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> on the day of Chriſts Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>And upon <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 55, 56. When they beheld the <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> and how the Body was laid, the Doctor ſays, that was on the ſixth day at night, (which (night) I cannot find in the word that it was at Night) and they returned, and prepared Spices and Ointments, and reſted the Sabbath day according to the Commandment; which is true, that they returned, prepared Spices, reſted, and kept the Sabbath, which was not A, but the Seventh-day-Sabbath after the Death of Chriſt, whilſt his Body was in the Grave, and he in Paradice (<hi>i. e.</hi>) in Heaven. But I know no word for that, that Chriſt was buried in the Night, but towards the end of the ſixth Day, and if it were not at Night, the Doctor ought not ſo to write.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48219:15"/>
            <p>And from <hi>Luke 24. 1. Matth. 28. 1. Mark 16. 1. John</hi> 20. 1. The Doctor would obſerve, <hi>p.</hi> 23. that the Sabbath according to their Account, did not end till towards the Morning of the next day, but it being not ſaid in either of thoſe places or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, that I find in the word, that the Sabbath did not end till towards the Morning, but that Chriſt was riſen when the Sabbath was paſt, <hi>Mark 16. 1. Early in the morning of the first day,</hi> ver. 2. This proves againſt him, as I think, that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was ended before, <hi>viz.</hi> the Evening before.</p>
            <p>And yet the Doctor ſays it is manifeſt, that at this time, as well the Sabbath as other days, were by them reckoned not from Evening to Evening, but rather according to the Roman account, from mid-night to mid-night.</p>
            <p>And to prove it, ſays, <hi>it was ſometime after the ninth hour</hi> ((i. e.) our three a Clock in the Afternoon) that Chriſt gave up the Spirit, <hi>Mark</hi> 15. 34, 37. and later, when they brake the Thieves Legs; and later, when <hi>Joſeph</hi> begged his Body, took it and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it, by which he would prolong the time to run it up into the Night, for which Night we find no Word, and for which I ſee no Reaſon, nor know any other to whom his ſence of this prolonged time is manifeſt, the general ſence of Learned Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians being as I think againſt him. All thoſe things being well conſiſtent before the Sabbath drew on, and our Lords giving up the Spirit, the begging of his Body, taking it and burying it, in a Tomb prepared, might all be in a very little time, for <hi>John 19. 42. The ſepulchre was nigh at hand,</hi> which ſurely was ſo little time as to be all finiſhed upon the Sixth day, before the Sabbath drew on, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 54, 55, 56. And for the Women to prepare Spices and Ointments the ſame Sixth day, and all before the Sun ſet.</p>
            <p>And this way of the Doctor's reaſoning, if it would hold, which I think it will not, would break in upon the Sabbath, upon which the Women reſted according to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Luke 23. 56, &amp;c.</hi> and would leave a doubt, whether the Sixth day were one of the Three days, unleſs men believe as the Doctor, that the days begin at mid-night; ſee Mr. <hi>Shepherd</hi>'s Tract on this Subject.</p>
            <p>The general opinion I think is right in this, that the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of days in the time of the Old Teſtament was from Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Evening, which reckoning I find not yet altered in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48219:15"/> Word; but the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were then Heathens, did reckon days from mid-night to mid-night.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 24. how long the Firſt day laſted is built on a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as if the day began at mid-night.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 25. he ſays, <hi>We reaſonably ſuppoſe from</hi> Luke 24. 29, 30, 35. <hi>that the two Diſciples from</hi> Emmaus <hi>came pretty late at night to</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>Which is but ſuppoſed, not in the Word, which Word is the Wiſdom of God, and the higheſt Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Ver. 29. They ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>abide with us, for it is towards evening, and the day is far ſpent,</hi> which might, and ſurely did leave time enough for them to return to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that day, for <hi>Luke 24. 33. They roſe up the ſame hour, and returned to</hi> Jeruſalem, which intimates their haſte in returning to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 'twas the ſame Day of the Reſurrection, that is, the Firſt Day of the Week, at Evening, that our Lord appeared to the Diſciples at <hi>Jeruſalem, John</hi> 20. 19. as they ſat at Meat, when the Doors were ſhut where the Diſciples were aſſembled for fear of the Jews, upon the Firſt day at Evening, and <hi>John</hi> 19. 40, 41, 42. The Body of Jeſus was laid in a Garden, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Jews Preparation day, for the Sepulchre was nigh at hand, and ſo no need of much time to bury him, all was eaſie to be finiſhed before the Sabbath began, to which the Sixth day was a Preparation day, which proves it to be the day before the Sabbath; yet the Doctor thinks it was about mid-night, and then infers as manifeſt, that the Jews and four Evangeliſts did reckon their days from mid-night to mid-night, and there adds, if they did not ſo reckon, Chriſt could not be ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 40. to be three Days and three Nights in the heart of the Earth, which I take it, is not well ſaid, for to make a doubt of the three Days in the Grave, unleſs we believe it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that the Jews and four Evangeliſts did reckon their days from mid-night to mid-night, ſeems very blamable.</p>
            <p>The Doctor thinks <hi>p.</hi> 26. the days in the time of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, reckoned from mid-night to mid-night; and from <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 6, 14, 15, 16. about the Paſſover that Evening <hi>v.</hi> 6. (or as in the Margent, between the two Evenings) is at mid-night, and that as ſoon as mid-night is paſt, Morning began, and ſays the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof, is ſo fair, as we need not ſcruple to embrace it.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48219:16"/>
            <p>And he thinks from the firſt born of <hi>Egypt</hi> being ſlain at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, that, the midnight began the next day after the Paſſover, then which he thinks nothing can be more clear, and <hi>p.</hi> 28. takes it to be very plain from what he has ſaid, <hi>That at the time of Chriſts Death and Reſurrection, the days were counted from mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night to mid-night,</hi> which matters which he thinks plain, clear, and manifeſt, I think are miſtaken by him.</p>
            <p>What was offered from <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5. the Evening and the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were the Firſt day, the Doctor thinks is eaſily anſwered, and renders it as in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and the Evening was, and the Morning was, one day (<hi>i. e.</hi>) ſays he, <hi>there was in the Firſt day, and ſo in the reſt, Evening and Morning, or Darkneſs and Light,</hi> which is ſo far true; and ſays, <hi>Darkneſs is put firſt, becauſe</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the Day from mid-night) <hi>the Dark is before the Light;</hi> but if it were ſo, which I think is not, then the Darkneſs would be after the Light, <hi>viz.</hi> till mid-night after, and would put Night and Day in Confuſion.</p>
            <p>To which I further ſay, as he, by day one, or one day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5. is there meant the Firſt day; and ſo I think in the New-Teſtament, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one day is generally meant the firſt day, and the firſt day is certainly meant, as to the day of Chriſts reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>But that the Evening in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5. began at midnight, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the current of learned men (Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 26.) and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Mr. <hi>Chafie,</hi> and contrary to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who beſt knew the meaning of the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and I think contrary to the Scriptures throughout, which begin the Evening when the Sun does ſet, <hi>Mark</hi> 1. 32. whereof more by and by.</p>
            <p>And as to the Evenings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 6. it ſeems to me, that one, or the Firſt Evening, was the Evening, which (after the Sun created) began the days (<hi>i. e.</hi>) when the Sun did ſet, and the other Evening was about the time of the daily and weekly Sacrifices, which ordinarily, I think, was about their ninth Hour, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) our three a Clock in the Afternoon, which <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 1. is called the ninth Hour, the Hour of Prayer, when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> went to the Temple.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Cornelius</hi> in a Viſion, ſaw an Angel about the ninth Hour, <hi>Acts</hi> 10, 3. And the ninth Hour, that is, our three a Clock in the Afternoon, was about the Hour of our Saviours being made a Sacrifice for his People, <hi>Matth. 27. 46. Mark</hi> 15. 34.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48219:16"/>
            <p>Or that other Evening might be, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 29, 36. when Mid-day was paſt.</p>
            <p>And (betwixt the two Evenings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 6.) is underſtood by many, to be betwixt the declining of the Sun after Noon, and the ſetting of the Sun, which may well be; but the firſt Evening began at Sun ſet, and belonged to the Day of the Week, which Days of the Week conſiſted of Evening and Morning, as before.</p>
            <p>Their Morning-Worſhip ſeems to have been about our nine a Clock in the Morning, which I think was their third Hour, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 4, 15. at which Hour the Holy Spirit was poured out.</p>
            <p>But the Evening of the Days of the Week after the Sun cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, I think began at, or about Sun ſet, and comprehended from Sun ſetting to Sun riſing, and the Morning, from Sun riſing to Sun ſet, which Evening and Morning made up every day of the Week then, and ever ſince as before.</p>
            <p>And yet the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 25. thinks, that both the Jews and four Evangeliſts did reckon their days from mid-night to mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Paſchal Lamb, Exod.</hi> 12. 3, 6. which was to be killed the Fourteenth day of the firſt Month, between the two Evenings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 2, 6. (whether the Evening wherein they were to kill it began at our three a clock in the Afternoon, or preſently after Noon) gave them time enough to kill it and dreſs it, without running up the time to mid-night.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, <hi>The Lord ſmote the firſt born of</hi> Aegypt <hi>at mid-night,</hi> ver. 29. and why it was at mid-night I know not, but (if we may ſo humbly ſay) it might be (<hi>inter alia</hi>) for greater terror to <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which mid-night there, did not that we find, alter the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Paſſover, much leſs did that ſmiting the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> alter the Days of the Week; and ſo our Lord obſerved the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover before his Paſſion with his Diſciples the Fourteenth Day of the firſt Month at Even, <hi>Matth. 26. 20. Mark. 14. 17. Luke</hi> 22. 7, 14.</p>
            <p>And we read, at Even there was upon the Tabernacle, as it were, the appearance of Fire, untill the Morning, and ſo, it was alway, and ſo the Evening did not here begin at mid-night, but as it began to be dark, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. 9, 15, 16, 21. that is, when the Sun did ſet.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48219:17"/>
            <p>Which Fire gave Light when it was Dark, that is, from the Evening till the Morning.</p>
            <p>And that the Evening does begin, not at mid-night, but at Sun ſet, we have many places in the Old and New-Teſtament, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 11. When the Evening cometh on, is, when the Sun is down; they are the words of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who wrote <hi>Geneſis</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Joſh. 10. 26, 27. The five Kings were hanged on five trees until the evening, and at the time of the going down of the ſun, they took them down by</hi> Joſhua'<hi>s command;</hi> ſo as the Evening was the time of the Suns going down in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s time.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 9. the Evening is called the Twilight, in the Twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Evening of the Day, and the Twilight begins when the Sun ſets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer. 6. 4. The day goeth away, for the ſhadows of the evening are ſtretched out;</hi> now when the Sun ſets the Earth begins to be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, and then the former day goeth away.</p>
            <p>Mark 1. 32. <hi>And at even when the ſun did ſet, they brought to him all that were diſeaſed,</hi> or the Evening being come when the Sun had ſet, which makes it as plain as words can well expreſs it, that the Evening began not at mid-night, but when the Sun did ſet, and that when <hi>Mark</hi> wrote his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Mark</hi> 13. 35. The Words of Chriſt, <hi>Watch, for ye know not when the maſter cometh, at even, or at mid-night, (or at cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crowing, or in the morning</hi>) ſo the Even was one time, and mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night another, ſo the Evening did not begin at mid-night, and yet the Doctor thinks it manifeſt, and that we need not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to embrace it, then which he thinks nothing can be more clear, whereas it ſeems very plain by the Scriptures, that every day begins in the Evening, that is, when the Sun ſets.</p>
            <p>And if it be ſo as above, then all which the Doctor ſays for mid-night-day, and all he builds thereon fails, which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm us that the Crucifying of Chriſt was on the Sixth day of the Week, about our three a Clock in the Afternoon, and that the Reſurrection was upon the Firſt day of the Week in the Morning; and yet the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 28. thinks it to be very plain, that at the time of Chriſts Death and Reſurrection, the Day began at mid-night, and did continue till mid-night.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48219:17"/>
            <p>And in <hi>p.</hi> 28. ſays, <hi>We have now found our Saviours Example as to the two firſt Sundays from his Reſurrection;</hi> if at leaſt their Firſt day of the Week be our Sunday, for the uncertainty of the days, which is the Firſt, and which is the Seventh day he ſtill holds, as before, as I think, againſt himſelf, for if our Sunday be not the Firſt day, why does he plead for it?</p>
            <p>By which, frequent reſerve of the uncertainty which is the Firſt day of the Week, if the Doctor does mean to rebuild the Firſt day (as the Romaniſts, and ſome few others) upon the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, or of the Civil Magiſtrate, it ſeems fair to tell us ſo, for if it be uncertain what day of the Week the Firſt day is, I cannot ſee any Foundation in the Word, or common Reaſon for obſerving an uncertain weekly Day, and if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, then it is certainly gone.</p>
            <p>As to our Saviours Example which the Doctor has found, as to one of thoſe two Firſt Sundays, it is an Example of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours, and two of his Diſciples travelling on Sunday, which Example I may allow him, without any hurt or danger to the main queſtion.</p>
            <p>And his other Example, about, after Eight days, which he has found, has been anſwered, as I think before.</p>
            <p>And theſe two Sundays, are all that the Doctor finds as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples by Chriſt, for altering the Sabbath from the Seventh to the Firſt day, of which altering we find not one word in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>He ſays nothing of any Word or Example of Chriſt before his Death, for ſuch alteration, for he knows our Saviours man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was to keep the Sabbath during his Life.</p>
            <p>Nor ſays he, that I remember, any thing of the Thief, his being with Chriſt in Paradice the ſame day of his Crucifixion, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 42, 43.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>p.</hi> 29. he ſays, <hi>We have clear Evidence of a like Practice,</hi> Acts 20. 7. And ſo leaps over all about <hi>Paul,</hi> and others keeping the Sabbath, that is in the former Chapters of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> which I ſhall have occaſion to remember him of.</p>
            <p>From which <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. he renders <hi>dielegeto,</hi> holding forth, and this rendring holding forth, the Doctor does twice, <hi>page</hi> 29.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:48219:18"/>
            <p>In the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 55<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in anſwer to the Objection from <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. where <hi>Paul</hi> Preached to the Diſciples, I take notice, that the Greek Word there rendred Preached, is in <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2. ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Reaſoned, where <hi>Paul,</hi> as his manner was, Preached to them three Sabbath-days; and ſo the ſame Greek word with that in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. is rendred Reaſoned in <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 4. where <hi>Paul</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Synagogue every Sabbath, to Jews and Gentiles, this little notice I take of the ſame Greek word in theſe three places of <hi>Acts 20. 7. Acts</hi> 18. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2. rendred Preached, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. but rendred Reaſoned, <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 4. and <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2. Though it be the ſame Greek word which I think of ſome uſe to ſhew that <hi>Paul</hi> preached Chriſt every Sabbath, the Doctor ſeems to take offence at, and gives leave to render it, <hi>Paul did hold forth,</hi> and inſtead of, <hi>he continued his Speech, that he held on his holding forth,</hi> till mid-night, which Expreſſion of holding forth has been much abuſed in this Age by ſome Men, againſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently Holy and Learned Non<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conforming Miniſters, when they have been accuſed as Malefactors for Preaching the Goſpel, to ſcorn, reproach, and deſpiſe them as holders forth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Expreſſion of Holding forth being taken in an ill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightful ſence by ſome, who ſo uſe it.</p>
            <p>I think the Doctor might have ſpared to put it upon <hi>Paul,</hi> who in his Preaching Chriſt, was then a Non-conformiſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and Preacher.</p>
            <p>And it ſeems, if it were not written incautelouſly to be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blamable.</p>
            <p>In which Expreſſions of Holding forth, with others after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which refer to Spiritual Praying and Praiſing, as this does to Preaching the Goſpel. The Doctor goes in bad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and I doubt, highly gratifies them, whilſt he writes ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably to their Language.</p>
            <p>Which words of the Doctor, however written with ſome ſeeming ſoftneſs, are a very ill Bleat if they were meant, which I hope they were not, as they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> commonly underſtood by all good and bad Men that I know.</p>
            <p>And in further Reply to the Doctor's from <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. I refer to what is in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 55. 56, 57, 58.</p>
            <p>And admitting that (one) there is one day, and that one day the Firſt day of the Week, and that the Diſciples there came to gether to break Bread, and admitting that breaking of Bread was the Lords Supper, and the Aſſembly there to be a Chriſtian
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48219:18"/> Aſſembly as it was, yet ſuppoſing the day as before, does not begin at mid-night, but in the Evening, as I think it certainly doth; and ſuppoſing <hi>Paul</hi> as his manner was <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2. (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) preached on the Sabbath, every Sabbath, <hi>Acts 18. 4. Acts</hi> 16. 30. and that to Jews and Gentiles, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 14, 42, &amp;c. which cannot be denied; and ſuppoſing that what we have in the Prophets reproving <hi>Iſrael</hi> for prophaning, or polluting (as <hi>Eſai. 56. 2, 4, 6. Eſai.</hi> 58. 13, &amp;c.) the Sabbath, or any part thereof, to be generally expreſſed by their refuſing to keep the Sabbath, and ſuppoſing what we have in the New-Teſtament about our Lords cuſtom of keeping the Sabbath to be briefly expreſſed, (by his going into the Synagogue on the Sabbath, and as preaching) does comprehend, and include all the reſt that was requiſite to the perfect keeping the Sabbath, as it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly did, or elſe we ſhould have read it there objected againſt him, which we do not find; and ſuppoſing the like of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in their meaſure in the <hi>Acts,</hi> &amp;c. about their keeping Sabbath, I think any Man may reaſonably ſuppoſe, that <hi>Paul</hi> who kept every Sabbath as before, had kept the Sabbath, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. And that when the Seventh day was over, <hi>Paul</hi> and the Diſciples met that Evening (that is, the Evening of the Firſt day) being ready to depart on the Morning (which Evening his readineſs to depart on the morrow ſeems to imply) which the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 31. thinks a pleaſant ſhift, which ſeems a plain and true Fact, for <hi>Paul</hi> there continued his Speech till mid-night, <hi>ver. 7, 8. And when he had recovered</hi> Eutichus, <hi>and broken bread, and eaten, and tarried a long while, till break of day,</hi> Paul <hi>did depart accordingly,</hi> Acts 20. 7, 11. And I know none has yet imagined that <hi>Paul</hi> and the Chriſtians kept two Sabbath days in one Week.</p>
            <p>So as ſuppoſing the Doctor's mid-night-day miſtaken, as I think it is, and ſuppoſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Firſt day to begin in the Evening, which I think it did, and does.</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſing <hi>Paul</hi>'s manner was to preach every Sabbath in the Synagogue, <hi>Acts 13. 14, 42. Acts 16. 30. Acts</hi> 18. 4. which he certainly did; and ſuppoſing that <hi>Paul</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s preaching in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue did comprehend his conſcientious obſerving the whole Sabbath day, then inſtead of a Preſident for the firſt Day, as the Doctor would make it, putting all thoſe places in the <hi>Acts</hi> together, it ſeems a Preſident for keeping the Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Sabbath, and the breaking Bread, and <hi>Paul</hi>'s preaching to the Diſciples there that Evening till mid-night, to be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48219:19"/> both after the Sabbath kept and ended, and his travelling the next Morning, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 11. if it were, as it ſeems, the Morning of the Firſt day after the Sabbath was over, makes it, that he did not keep the Firſt day, but travelled upon it. So ſuppoſing as before the breaking of Bread, imports the Lords Supper, which the Diſciples came together for, upon the Firſt day of the Week, that might very well ſucceed <hi>Paul</hi>'s and their keeping the Sabbath before, upon the Evening of which Firſt day the Converted might come together to receive the Lords Supper to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when they were diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the Aſſembly (as is uſual in our Aſſemblys to this day) to whom <hi>Paul</hi> preached Chriſt upon the Sabbath day before, and departed in the Morning, read and judge, and this is the clear Evidence, which the Doctor ſays he has from <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7.</p>
            <p>And the Doctor thinks I am not in earneſt, and calls it tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling and ſhifting, (which are hard Words) to render <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one day of the Week, from which I ſee no inconvenience when he renders it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one, which ſignifies one, yet was the Firſt day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5. and when he himſelf renders <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one, <hi>p.</hi> 42 and when it is agreed, that tho' <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly ſignifies one, which no Grammarian can deny, yet that one was the Firſt day, and ſo by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. I think may be meant the Firſt day of the Week, tho' the <hi>Greek</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one, be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred one Scores of times in the New-Teſtament.</p>
            <p>I paſs by the Doctor's caſe of a Horſe bought for five Pounds, and paid by five Pounds of Candles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe I have no mind to that way of arguing, by telling old Tales; <hi>p.</hi> 32. he goes over again the caſe of the Paſſover, the days of Crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Reſurrection, and <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7. to all which before, and <hi>p.</hi> 33. the caſe of <hi>Abel, Enoch, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and from thence till <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s coming out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> he ſays, <hi>I bring no other proof for their keeping the Sabbath, but</hi> Exod. 5. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>And if he mean that I bring no other Proof, but one Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Proof, that ſeems ſomewhat hardly meant.</p>
            <p>And he may find in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> and here before, other Proofs beſides <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>But I had thought one plain, full Word of God for <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s there keeping Sabbath, or for proving any other Truth, or Matter of Fact, had been enough to convince the moſt Learned, who acknowledge the Divine Authority of the Scriptures, which I hope the Doctor does and I do.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48219:19"/>
            <p>What the Doctor would <hi>p.</hi> 34. teach me, as to better purpoſe for the Seventh-day-Sabbath, from <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s ſeven fat and lean Kine, and the ſeven days before <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood, and <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi>'s being ſeven Years at Graſs, and from the three Intervals of ſeven days, one about the Rain before the Flood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 4. and the other two of <hi>Noah</hi>'s ſtaying ſeven days, and then again ſeven days before he ſent out the Dove, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 10, 12. which he ſays is better Argument then any I bring.</p>
            <p>I hope he will not oblige me or any other to believe he ſo thinks, for if thoſe his Arguments be better then any I bring, I doubt he would not have writ this Book at his Age to Anſwer them.</p>
            <p>P. 34, 35. he ſays, <hi>There is nothing of a weekly Sabbath in</hi> Job, <hi>which if it were true, needs not, if there be, as there is enough for it elſewhere, in the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if you will allow a little Digreſſion, ſee <hi>Job</hi> 31. 26, 27, 28. which the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 64. ſays, <hi>may perhaps be</hi> Job's <hi>diſclaimer of Sun-Worſhip, which is ſomewhat towards it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſee that of <hi>Eliphaz, Job 22. 17, 22. Receive I pray thee, the law at his mouth,</hi> that is Gods Mouth, where the word Law, is the ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word uſed <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 28. about the Sabbath, and <hi>Job 22. 22. Lay up his words in thine heart,</hi> ſo as whenever, and where-ever <hi>Job</hi> lived, tis certain, he and his Friends had ſome knowledge of the Law, and Words of God, and if of the Law and Words of God, why not of the Sabbath which is his Word, and a part of his Law: See alſo <hi>Job 1. 1, 5, 6, 8, 9. Job</hi> 2. 1, 3. eſpecially <hi>Job</hi> 1. 6. and <hi>Job</hi> 2. 1. which day, at leaſt ſome of the <hi>Hebrew Rabbies</hi> thought to be the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>And although the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 35. would make all that is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> that the Aſcenſion of Chriſt might be upon the Sabbath day, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 12. to be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle matter, and yet ſerving my turn, I refer the Reader for that to the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 43. to which I add, I do not yet ſee, but that the Aſcenſion day might be upon the Sabbath day, according to <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 12. for I do not think thoſe words, that <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> (the place of his Aſcenſion) <hi>is from Jeruſalem a ſabbath-days-jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> Acts 1. 12. which of old was eſteemed about two Miles, are ſo expreſſed there by the Holy Spirit, but for ſome ſpecial reſpect to the Sabbath day, which words of a Sabbath-days-jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney are no where elſe ſo expreſſed in the Scriptures, that I find, but I take it tis agreed by Geographers, that <hi>Mount Olivet</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48219:20"/> two Miles from <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> In <hi>Exod. 16. 29. The Lord giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you on the ſixth day, the bread of two days, abide every man in his place, let no man go out of his place on the ſeventh day,</hi> that is, that day they were not to go abroad into the Field to gather <hi>Manna,</hi> nor to do any other Work, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. but they might go to the Holy Convocation, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23. 3. And the Cities of the <hi>Levites</hi> were to reach 2000 Cubits from without the City, Eaſt, South, Weſt, North, <hi>Numb.</hi> 35. 5. and in <hi>Joſh.</hi> 3. 3, 4. when the Ark was born towards <hi>Jordan,</hi> the People were to go after it, yet there was to be a ſpace between them, and it about 2000 Cubits by meaſure, and they were not to come nearer to it; what thoſe Cubits in meaſure did extend to, the Jews could beſt tell us, who thought it about two Miles, which thoſe in the Camp might travel to the Ark, the place of their Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon the Sabbath day, <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 43. 44, 45. And it ſeems to me, that <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 12. is ſo expreſſed, to ſhew that Chriſt and his Diſciples going from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> and the Diſciples going from thence back again to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was no breach of the Sabbath day.</p>
            <p>But however this were, I think the main queſtion, which is the true Chriſtian Sabbath is built and eſtabliſhed upon many other direct full Scriptures before and after cited, which give no colour for denying.</p>
            <p>What the Doctor offers for the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt, Acts 2. 1. p.</hi> 37. as to the day when it was, which he thinks was on the Firſt day of the Week, I know no Word for that, or other Ground but Conjectures, and ſome uncertain <hi>Romiſh</hi> Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for what day the Fiftieth day was from the true day on which Chriſt and his Diſciples kept the Paſſover, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 17, 18, 19, 20. I do not yet ſo certainly know, and the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 12. agrees, that our Saviour kept his laſt Paſſover on one day, and the Jews on another: But the moſt probable Judgment I can make from <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 17, 18, 19, 20. from <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 12. and <hi>Acts 13. Acts 16. Acts 17. Acts 18. 4, &amp;c.</hi> is, that it might be on the Sabbath day, and this is certain, that when the day of Pentecoſt was fully come, the Holy Spirit was poured out, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 1. 2. But ſuppoſing what the Doctor agrees <hi>p.</hi> 12. that Chriſt kept it one day, and the Jews on another, I think I can prove by the Word, that Pentecoſt was on the Seventh-day-Sabbath, and not upon the firſt day of the Week.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:48219:20"/>
            <p>But this alſo about what day it was, not being yet ſo evident to all, and the Sabbath being, as I think, clearly proved by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Texts, I paſs it by at preſent.</p>
            <p>I pretermit divers things to which he recurs, <hi>p.</hi> 38. and takes up again and again what he had written to before, and then the Doctor adds,</p>
            <p>A like place is that of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now concerning the collection for the Saints, as I have given order to the Churches of</hi> Galatia, <hi>even ſo do ye upon the firſt day of the week, let every one of you lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered him, that there be no gathering when I come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What likeneſs there is between thoſe two places I can ſee very little of, and that this yields nothing at all for his purpoſe, any man who will read it twice may eaſily diſcern, yet he thinks it is plain from thence, that the Frſt day of the Week was week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved, and was wont to be obſerved, both by the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and by the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> which he thinks <hi>Paul</hi> ſuppoſes, and takes for granted, which are all meer Conjectures where I think <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may well be rendred one day of the Week, without any offence.</p>
            <p>To which place I think there is anſwer, <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 58. 59. to which I add,</p>
            <p>If the Doctor by the Words was weekly obſerved, and wont to be obſerved, mean was weekly, and wont to be obſerved as a Sabbath, or as a weekly Day of Holy Reſt (without which he ſays nothing).</p>
            <p>I reply, that here is not one word of any Sabbath or Reſt weekly, or other Reſt, or of any Worſhip or Preaching, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch thing, not one ſuch word, either at <hi>Corinth</hi> or <hi>Galatia,</hi> or taking it for granted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the quite contrary, that is, an order that they ſhould every one of them lay by in ſtore for charitable Uſes, which does include the caſting up their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, how elſe could they know how God had proſpered them, which the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 39. ſays ſcornfully, is a wiſe Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which ſeems a true and plain Matter of Fact.</p>
            <p>What that order was to the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> he ſays, that I cannot tell, but leaves out my next words, <hi>unleſs it were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Poor;</hi> and to what is in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 58. about an yearly Collection, I add, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 1, 2. where he ſaid <hi>Achaia</hi> was ready a year ago, and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 10. others were forward a year ago.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48219:21"/>
            <p>But admitting that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here ſignifies Firſt, here is not one word in this order to keep Holy the Firſt day, nothing of that day as a Sabbath, nothing of Praiſes, breaking Bread, Praying or Preaching, or of any Worſhip, or Reſting here, but only an order for every one of the Chriſtians there, <hi>to lay by him in ſtore as God had proſpered him,</hi> which ſeems alſo, when they were aſunder, and at home, that there might be no gathering when <hi>Paul</hi> came; and this I ſhould think any who read it (without great prejudice) muſt needs ſee and know; ſo that for the Doctor to ſay he thinks it plain there, that the Firſt day was weekly obſerved, and wont to be obſerved at <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> and that <hi>Paul</hi> takes it for granted, and ſuppoſeth it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without any word for it, ſeems all from a ſtrong and willing fancy, and very blameable, as highly impoſing on the World.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>p.</hi> 38. and 39. he reaſſumes what he had written to before, which in me, without any great cauſe that I know, he <hi>p.</hi> 39. calls trifling, and Childs-play, which ſhews him to be angry, and <hi>p.</hi> 41. ſays, <hi>It muſt be great Ignorance, or ſomewhat worſe,</hi> which ſort of Language agrees well enough in this Cauſe to prop it up (inſtead of Word and Argument) with hard Expreſſions, and if that will pleaſe him I ſhall eaſily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my Ignorance and Weakneſſes, which are many and great: but withal, I think a weak and ſimple Man who has the word and command of God on his ſide, as I think I cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have in this caſe, may contend with the moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for whom otherwiſe I yield my ſelf much too weak.</p>
            <p>Nor do I find in all his Book any reaſon, much leſs any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe (as he <hi>p.</hi> 42, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) that the Firſt day was then ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally obſerved, or wont to be obſerved, or at all obſerved, unleſs by the Heathens, nor that it was according to Chriſts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, becauſe we have no word that I know for either, which word is the higheſt Reaſon, and why then does the Doctor top upon others thoſe Words, According to Chriſt's Direction.</p>
            <p>And a like ſaying of the Doctor's we have <hi>p.</hi> 43. by Chriſts giving commandments to the Apoſtles, about things pertaining to the Kingdom of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 2, 3. that we are to preſume this in particular, about the obſerving the Firſt day of the Week, and yet there confeſſeth what thoſe Commandments were in particular we cannot tell, ſo we are to preſume what he admits we cannot tell, which to me is a new Article in Religion made
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48219:21"/> for this purpoſe. And upon ſuch Preſumptions without one word from Chriſt that I know, the Doctor's opinion ſeems built.</p>
            <p>P. 41. He conſiders <hi>Mark 2. 28. The Son of Man is Lord alſo of the Sabbath,</hi> and ſuppoſeth by Son of Man, is there meant Chriſt, and if he ſuppoſe it, why then does he there controvert it; which Text ſhews the Sabbath to be the Lords Day, as <hi>ver. 27. The Sabbath was made for man,</hi> ſhews it was made for the good of Man, for his Spiritual and Eternal good.</p>
            <p>And ſays, <hi>I can't ſhew that ever the Jewiſh Sabbath is called the Lords day,</hi> although he knows if he have read the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 64, 65, 66, 67. that I there quote divers Scriptures, where the Lords Seventh day is called the Lords Day, whereof more by and by, upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
            <p>What he ſays <hi>p.</hi> 43. that I cannot tell whether of the two (that is the Seventh or the Firſt day) is the Seventh day of the Week, does again overturn all his Book, for if it be as he ſays, uncertain, ſo as we know not which day is which, how can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man obſerve his day in Faith, and what is not of Faith is Sin, and what then is become of all his Arguments for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain weekly Firſt day?</p>
            <p>But I think we can tell which is the Seventh-day-Sabbath, and I ſay as before, from <hi>Nehe.</hi> 9. 13, 14. that <hi>the Lord made known to them his Sabbaths,</hi> his Sabbaths, ſo the Sabbath was the Lords Day, which they knew; and from him and them we have his Sabbaths. And <hi>Rom. 3. 2. to the Jews were committed the words of God,</hi> which with the Old-Teſtament, and therein the Ten Commands they ſtill have; and I think we ought to believe what the Lord Chriſt accounted and named to be the Sabbath day, was then, and I think is now his Sabbath-day, that is, the Lords Day, <hi>Mark</hi> 2. 28.</p>
            <p>P. 44. 45, 46. <hi>Rev. 1. 10. I was in the Spirit on the Lords day,</hi> which he would have to be on the Firſt day, which I think I have ſhewn by the Scriptures, <hi>Enquiry,</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 64. to 68. to be the Seventh day, to which I do not remember he offers any anſwer (unleſs ſome Traditions) to which, to avoid Tautologies, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader, and am of the ſame opinion as there, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Prejudice, which he would often inſinuate, I think, the Lords Day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 10. was not only the name of a day, but the name of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, <hi>Gen. 2. 2, 3, 4. Exod. 20. 10. Deut. 5. 14. Iſaiah 58. 13. Matth. 12. 8. Mark. 2. 28. Luke</hi> 6. 5. which Scriptures
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48219:22"/> he that will examine and conſider, may eaſily ſee that the Seventh-day-Sabbath is the Lords Day, (if the Scriptures be as they ought to be, the rule of judging in this caſe) which the Doctor would fain have to be the Firſt day, and cannot tell us which day of the Week, the Firſt day is now from Chriſts time as before, and does not know it, and thinks it impoſſible to know it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 46. 47. he again admits, <hi>That Christ was the God who gave the Commandments,</hi> by which he does admit, <hi>that the ſeventh day there given by Christ is the Lords day,</hi> for <hi>Exod. 20. 10. the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day is the ſabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> (i. e.) the Seventh day is the Lords day. And ſo it often falls out in this debate, that what he and others are conſtrained to admit in one point, anſwers what they would deny in another, as I think this does; for if the Lord gave the Commandments, as he did, and as the Doctor admits (together with the Father and Holy Spirit) then he gave the Fourth Command, and therein the Seventh day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 10. which Seventh day is there expreſly ſaid to be the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, that is, to be the Lords day, which as I think by his own admiſſion, tells us, which is the Lords day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
            <p>Of his Traditions, <hi>p.</hi> 48. 49. (on which the Doctor before) I think there is or can be no certainty from them.</p>
            <p>And their Authority to alter any thing in Doctrinals or Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals, ſtated in the Scriptures is of no force with me, nor with any Proteſtant that I know, nor I hope with him, and he may ſee in the <hi>Enquiry</hi> divers Traditions, Hiſtories, and Records for the Seventh-day-Sabbath, which the Doctor anſwers not, although I build all upon the Scriptures, and not on Traditions.</p>
            <p>I ſay as before, that Chriſts manner was not to keep A, but The Sabbath during his Life, and the Women, and others kept it, whilſt his Body reſted in the Grave, whilſt he was in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, that is, in Heaven; not only on what they called the Sabbath, as the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 50. which I think not well ſurmiſed by him (as if they, or rather the Holy Spirit there called a wrong day the Sabbath) but on what was the Sabbath, and that ſome of the Diſciples travelled upon the very Reſurrection day, and that <hi>Paul</hi> and other Chriſtians did not only ſeem to (which are the Doctor's words, and I think are hard words) but expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and actually did obſerve, not only what they called the Sabbath, but what was the Sabbath, the true Seventh day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath (not only) after Chriſts Reſurrection, but after his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48219:22"/> and after the Holy Spirit given, and that that was <hi>Paul</hi>'s manner, and of others every Sabbath day as before, theſe Repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I am forced to.</p>
            <p>Which I think, do prove that Chriſt and the Apoſtles did then take not A, but The Seventh day to be the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath (as it was); or why elſe doth the Holy Spirit ſo very often in the four Evangeliſts, before his Death and Reſurrection, and in the <hi>Acts</hi> after his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, and after the pouring out the Holy Spirit, name it not A, but The Sabbath, not only what they called, but what was the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Yet the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 51. thinks <hi>Paul</hi>'s Preaching upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath days to be occaſional, by which, if he means as it there ſeems occaſional only, I know no word he has from God in the Scriptures, for his Sence of occaſional, and I think <hi>Paul</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Practice to Preach upon the Sabbath days, was according to the Duty of a Miniſter of Chriſt, and in Obedience to Chriſts expreſs Command, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19, 20. by which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand I think all other his Miniſters are obliged.</p>
            <p>And as to the Paſſover, and all Sacrifices, and other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials, that they are aboliſhed by the Death of Chriſt, I think certain, and to what is ſaid in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> as to that, I add this,</p>
            <p>That the Paſſover, ſacrifices are all ſet aſide by that word, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 19. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23, 24, 25, 26. <hi>This do in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me,</hi> and ſo the Paſſover, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are laid aſide by the Lords Supper, by which Ordinance of the Supper, we declare that Chriſt was ſacrificed for the Sins of his People, and by this we declare his Death till he come in Glory, to judge the Quick and Dead; and there was, or is no further need of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, or Types to repreſent Chriſts Death. And ſo the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover, and all other Sacrifices to be at an end, by theſe words, <hi>This is my body which is given for you, or which is broken for you, this do in remembrance of me.</hi> Which Lords Supper was then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and immediately ſucceeded the Paſſover, which Paſſover then ceaſed, <hi>Matth. 26. 17, 20, 26. And as they were eating, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus took bread,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mark 14. 22, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to what is offered <hi>p.</hi> 54. from <hi>Rom. 14 4, 5, 6. He that regardeth a day, regardeth it to the Lord, and he that regardeth not the day to the Lord, he doth not regard it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:48219:23"/>
            <p>It is not ſaid what was the day there in queſtion, but the Doctor thinks it moſt likely to be that of the Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
            <p>What day this was, is hard for any Man at this diſtance of time to determine, and more hard to build any certain Doctrine upon it, as a certain Day, when God has not that I know, told us in his Word what day it was, but left it wholly uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p>I find nothing in that Epiſtle about days, till <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 4, 5, 6. where one Man eſteemed one Day before another, another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed every day, <hi>he that regardeth the day, regardeth it to the Lord, and he that regardeth not the day to the Lord, he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is not there ſaid (as the Doctor acknowledges <hi>p.</hi> 54.) what was the Day there, nor do I now ſee how poſſibly to know what Weekly, or Monthly, or Yearly, or Feaſting, or Faſting, or other day it did refer to, but of the Sabbath there is no mention, and why is it then moſt likely to be the Sabbath, which he confeſſes is not there ſaid, and whatever day it was, it ſeems it was no great matter whether they regarded it or not, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>And whatever day that were, it was certainly ſuch a day as <hi>Paul</hi> would not have them judge one another for, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. which makes it likely to me, that it was not the Sabbath day which <hi>Paul</hi> ſo conſtantly preached Chriſt upon, and obſerved as before, which Sabbath is a part of that Moral Law which <hi>Paul</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to God, but was ſuch a day (whatever day it was) as he thought fit at that time and place to leave undetermined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for</hi> Gal. 4. 3, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> Galatia <hi>were ſome Diſciples,</hi> Acts 18. 1, 4, 23. In which Chapter it is ſaid, <hi>Paul preached at</hi> Corinth <hi>every ſabbath, to Jews and Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1. 2. directs that Epiſtle to the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> where probably were ſome converted, and many uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Gal. 4. 3. Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>When we were children, we were in bondage under the Elements, or under the Rudiments of the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which ſeems the Heathen World, <hi>ver. 8. When they knew not God, they did ſervice to them, who they knew by nature were no Gods,</hi> which was the caſe of the Heathens, for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did then,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48219:23"/> and do ſtill Worſhip Jehovah, who is God, the true God, and ſo do actually Worſhip Chriſt the only Meſſiah, who is Jehovah, as in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 9, &amp;c. <hi>And the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are one Jehovah,</hi> Deut. 6. 4, 5. Enquiry p. 12. <hi>But the Iſraelites don't yet know Chriſt to be Johovah, their Meſſiah, Saviour, and Redeemer;</hi> which Truth upon their Converſion and Reſtoration, remains to be revealed to them.</p>
            <p>So as this place ſeems ſpecially directed to thoſe who had an Heatheniſh Education, who before ſerved thoſe who were no Gods, who after they knew God, <hi>Gal. 4. 9. were turning again to the weak and beggarly Rudiments, to their firſt Teachings, and Heatheniſh Inſtruction,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> there blames <hi>ver. 10. you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve days, and months, and times, and years,</hi> ver. 11. <hi>I am afraid of you, leaſt I have beſtowed upon you labour in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What days theſe were is the Queſtion, the Doctor ſays tis not here ſaid in particular, what thoſe days were that are here meant, yet he thinks it is moſt likely, and ſcarce to be doubted, to be meant of the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That I think days there cannot be meant of a weekly Reſt, and if it be, it is directed there not to reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sunday, which was obſerved by the Heathens in honour of the Sun, as we may ſee afterward.</p>
            <p>And every Sabbath being obſerved by <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Sabbath not being (that I can find) in queſtion, days there I think can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refer to the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Which the Doctor thinks moſt likely to be meant of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, though he acknowledges it is not ſaid; and if it be not ſo ſaid, how can any mans Conſcience build upon what is not ſaid in the Word, and the Heathens generally obſerved Sunday, and their Princes and Magiſtrates being Heathens, ſome of thoſe converted to the Chriſtian Faith, might in ſome ſort decline giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them offence upon their days, whether Feaſtivals or Faſting days, but that tho it might be is conjectural. 'Tis certain that many do things now which relate to Worſhip, in complyance with thoſe under whom they live, and ſo have done I doubt in former Ages, and tis certain they obſerved days, which obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Paul</hi> blamed, and ſome of thoſe days might alſo be Jewiſh days, as Paſſover, New Moons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> or <hi>days<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of purim,</hi> Heſter 9. 26. which the Jews obſerve ſtill, as I think, in all Nations where they live.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48219:24"/>
            <p>And tis to me moſt likely, and ſcarce to be doubted, that one of thoſe days blamed by <hi>Paul,</hi> and the principal one was Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, which the Heathens obſerved, wherein the converted Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were by their Heathen Parents who knew not God, firſt inſtructed before they knew God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 8. which <hi>Paul</hi> calls weak, and beggarly Elements, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. which words of weak and Beggarly Elements do certainly not refer to any part of the Moral Law, as afterward.</p>
            <p>So that upon the whole of this in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 9, 10, 11. it ſeems more likely, that <hi>Paul</hi> blames them for obſerving the Firſt day, if it were at all then obſerved by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 12. which is the next verſe, <hi>Paul</hi> adds, <hi>Brethren, I beſeech you to be as I am,</hi> who conſtantly obſerved the Sabbath day as before.</p>
            <p>As to what is objected from <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 16. where <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>Let no man judge you, in meat or in drink, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new moon, or of the Sabbaths, Greek,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 55, 56, 57, 58. underſtands of Sabbaths, and ſo of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, and <hi>p.</hi> 59. does not think it by the Fourth Command to be ſo determined to this day, that is, the Seventh day, as to be unchangeable to after Ages: And when Chriſt, or his Apoſtles by direction from him did put it into a new order; this new order doth as well ſuit the words of the Fourth Command as that former, all which are <hi>poſtulata,</hi> and I reply, if it be not changed, then the Doctor cannot change it; and if it be ſettled in the Word, that the Seventh day is the Sabbath, as I think it is, then it is unchangeable, and the Doctor cannot ſuit the Command to his Senſe, and when the Doctor (or any other) produceth any ſuch new order from Chriſt, or from his Apoſtles to change the Seventh to the Firſt day, he will ſay ſomewhat, and I hope all Chriſtians will obey it, but I ſee not yet any ſuch new order produced.</p>
            <p>In the General, I acknowledge this of <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 16. at firſt ſeemed the moſt colourable Objection that I knew.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coloſſe</hi> is ſaid to be in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> and the Inhabitants Heathens, this Epiſtle <hi>Coloſſ. 1. 1, 2. Paul</hi> directs to the Saints, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Brethren in Chriſt, which are at <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> which it ſeems were converted Heathens, and it may be ſome perſecuted and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Jews, <hi>ver. 9. 10. Paul</hi> prays for them, <hi>that they may be fruitful in every good work, of which good work the law of God is a rule,</hi> and <hi>ver. 13, 14, 15, 16. Paul</hi> tells them, <hi>that the ſon of God the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48219:24"/> created all things,</hi> whom <hi>ver.</hi> 3. he calls the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>to whom thoſe who were enemies by wicked works</hi> (which wicked Works I think were Works againſt the Moral Law) <hi>were then reconciled to preſent them,</hi> ver. 22. <hi>holy, and unblameable, and unreproveable in his ſight, (free from all Immoralities) and preſent them perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, whom as they had received, ſo they ſhould walk in him,</hi> which good Works Perfection, receiving Chriſt, and holy Walking, I think were true Converſion, ſincere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Faith, Holineſs, and new Obedience to the Word of God and Moral Law.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Coloſſ. 2. 8. Beware leaſt any man ſpoil you, through Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the World, and not after Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Philoſophers (who are thought to have been Platoniſts) would then, as others now, have brought the Doctrine of Chriſt, and Laws of his Kingdom, to be judged by their Reaſon, who were Heathens, who would have put a cheat upon them by their Traditions, to withdraw them from Chriſts inſtitutions, after the Rudiments, or firſt Teachings of the Heatheniſh World, which were corrupt.</p>
            <p>The Heathens had other Objects, (as Sun, Moon, and Stars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and ways of Worſhip, contrary to Chriſt and his Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new moon, or of the ſabbaths (or weeks</hi>) Coloſſ. 2. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let no man judge or cenſure you, or impoſe upon you, that as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is not after Chriſt and his Laws;</hi> there were Feaſtivals among the Jews which were Typical and Ceremonial, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Heathens which were Idolatrous.</p>
            <p>Againſt which Rudiments of the World, <hi>ver. 8. Paul</hi> ſpeaks more from <hi>ver.</hi> 20. to 23. to which <hi>Paul</hi> would have them dead, and not as tho living in the World, (which was there Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh) to be ſubject to Ordinances after the Commandments and Doctrines of Men (of Heatheniſh Men) which things have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a ſhew of Wiſdom in Will-Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Which ſecond Chapter ſeems mainly aimed againſt the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Heatheniſh World, and their Will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Worſhip, after the Commandments and Doctrines of Heatheniſh Men.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:48219:25"/>
            <p>Though ſome Learned Men have alſo thought, that it refers to the inclinations of ſome there to the Ceremonial Laws, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the Death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now that the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Sabbaths, does ſignifie Week, or Weeks, I refer to the <hi>Enquiry, p. 70, 71, 72, 73. John 20. 1, 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Luke</hi> 24. 1. the like 16. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in the plural number doth ſignify Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, or Weeks, and in the New Teſtament is uſed for Week, and for Sabbath, whether it be put there for Weeks I cannot now examine, nor do I ſee it neceſſary, ſeeing the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber does ordinarily ſignifie more then one.</p>
            <p>What I offered in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 70. that the word Sabbaths in the New Teſtament is never applyed to the weekly Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-Sabbath, was miſtaken by me, and the word never, ſhould have been left out, or the Expreſſion otherways cured; and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry p.</hi> 136. that God who reſerved a Tenth of our Subſtance, reſerved, But, a Seventh of our Time, But, ſhould have been left out.</p>
            <p>Both which, with other Errata's before, I read it in any Printed Book, I gave particular order to amend, in a Printed Paper of Errata's, and upon a queſtion which requires ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, by ſo old and weak a Man as I am, beſides Errors in Tranſcribing, and Printing under ſome Difficulties, it will be ſtrange if there be not now committed more and greater Errors, which a little Candour and Temper would eaſily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 45. the Doctor takes a third exception, and writes near half a page upon it, on a ſimilitude I uſe of <hi>Moſes, no man knows of his Sepulchre to this day,</hi> that is, no Man ever knew where his Sepulchre was.</p>
            <p>And as to the Similitude or Compariſon referring to the day of Chriſts Incarnation, the Doctor would rather ſay, at this day then (as I) to this day, which great Exception can hardly be excuſed, for in that ſimilitude I think he miſtakes my words, and meaning alſo.</p>
            <p>At the Incarnation ſome then knew the day tho no Man At this day knows what day it was, and the Doctor agrees the day of the Week, or Year, of Chriſts Incarnation is now not known ſo as this Exception of to, againſt at, ſeems very little at beſt.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:48219:25"/>
            <p>And I think he knows that the Lord buried <hi>Moſes</hi> in a Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre unknown, not only at that time, but to this day, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. 6.</p>
            <p>Now tis true the Greek word Sabbath, in the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in the New Teſtament is alſo applyed to the Sabbath, as to the Week, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 15, 10, 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and 28. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the plural number, (from the Greek word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Sabbath, in the ſingular number) is in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſometimes underſtood of the Sabbath, and ſometimes of the Week, and in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 1. properly meant of both.</p>
            <p>And ſo the queſtion remains, Whether Sabbaths <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 2. 16. ought to be rendred Sabbaths, or Sabbath, or Weeks, and if Sabbaths, Whether the Seventh day be there meant, or no?</p>
            <p>The Doctor thinks Sabbaths here muſt be meant of the Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-Sabbaths (which words, muſt be one very poſitive, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Opinion of many Learned, as by and by) which he thinks it manifeſt, <hi>p. 56. were there in diſpute,</hi> (which diſpute I cannot find in that Epiſtle, nor any where elſe in the Word) and why then does the Doctor without the Word think it to be there in diſpute, and manifeſt? and he thinks it was then at an End, (which End we read not in the Word) but find it ſtill obſerved in many Churches of Chriſt to this day, <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 106. to 112, 118, 119, 120.) and why then does he think it was then at an end.</p>
            <p>Nor do I find any new order from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, as he ſurmiſes, <hi>p.</hi> 59.</p>
            <p>And if Sabbaths, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 16. do mean Weeks, and not the Weekly Sabbath day, then that Objection of the Doctor falls, and if it mean the Firſt day (<hi>i. e.</hi>) Sunday, which the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens obſerved, then it is againſt the Doctor ſo far as <hi>Paul</hi>'s bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their judging will go.</p>
            <p>And if it mean Weeks, as it ſeems to me more likely it ought to be here rendred, or if it means Ceremonial Sabbaths, then ſo far as this reaches it refers to the Obſervation of Weeks, and Ceremonial Sabbaths now aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>But both one and other ſeem to me uncertain now, to build any (muſt be's) upon.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48219:26"/>
            <p>And <hi>Coloſſ. 2. 16. Let no man judge you in reſpect of a feaſtival, or of the new moon, or of the ſabbaths.</hi> Beſide the Seventh-day-Sabbath, there were at leaſt three Feaſtivals or Sabbaths amongſt the Jews.</p>
            <p>At the Paſſover, the Feaſt of Unleavened Bread ſeven Days, from which Paſſover, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23. 4, 5. we have the pretence for <hi>Eaſther,</hi> now ceaſed as before.</p>
            <p>The Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> fifty days after the Paſſover, that is, ſeven Weeks after, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. 16. where we have the pretence for <hi>Whitſuntide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were alſo the Sabbaths of Years, <hi>every ſeventh year ſhall be a ſabbath of reſt unto the Land, a ſabbath for the Lord,</hi> Lev. 25. 4. <hi>And after ſeven ſabbaths of years,</hi> ver. 8. <hi>they were to ſound the trumpet of the Jubilee,</hi> ver. 9. <hi>and ye ſhall hallow, or ſanctifie the fiftieth year,</hi> ver. 10. And hence (as I take it) we have the ground of the <hi>Roman</hi> Jubilees.</p>
            <p>Now it ſeems to me, that if the word there do mean Sabbaths, that thoſe three may be blotted out, and taken out of the way, and all Heatheniſh Feaſts, Feaſtivals, Weeks, and Sabbaths, as well Sunday as the reſt, <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
            <p>But that which I think does fairly and fully anſwer the whole Objection from <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2. 16. beſides what is hereafter offered by Learned Men, may be, that this is a caution againſt judging the Believers at <hi>Coloſſe, in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of the Feaſtivals, new moons, or ſabbaths,</hi> and ſeems to agree with <hi>Rom. 14. 4, 5, 6. Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant, one man eſteemeth one day above another, another eſteemeth every day,</hi> and at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> were then cautious againſt judging the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans about days.</p>
            <p>And we find not in either of thoſe Epiſtles one word to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Seventh day to the Firſt, or to inſtitute the Firſt, all that would be a forced interpretation, the Text is againſt judging of Chriſtians there about days.</p>
            <p>And whether it be meant at that time and place, of judging for or againſt thoſe Meats and Drinks, or Days or Feaſts, or Faſts, or Weeks, or Sabbaths, whatever they were is not now over eaſie to be reſolved.</p>
            <p>'Tis likely ſome converted Teachers, whether Jews or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, I know not, had taught what was not right about Days, which <hi>Paul</hi> here corrects.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:48219:26"/>
            <p>And tis certain there are ſome things in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles hard to be underſtood, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16. and if they were hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in <hi>Peter</hi>'s time, which was <hi>Paul</hi>'s time, for they were Contemporaries, much more hard now near 1700 Years after; and by whom hard places in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles were then wreſted, we may gather a little light, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as were not ſubject to the Law of God, were the wreſters, and this place in <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. ſeems ſtrongly wreſted beyond the words of it, which are againſt judging the Saints at <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> in thoſe reſpects at that time, when the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel had much to do to preach Chriſt, and by Chriſt to lay the foundations of chriſtianity, which foundation in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Redeemer and Creator of all things,</hi> Paul <hi>ſoundly laid in this Epiſtle,</hi> Coloſſ. 2. 3, 14, 16.</p>
            <p>Which Caution againſt judging one another, was, no doubt, at that time and place neceſſary, and rightly underſtood, is ſtill of great uſe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>let no man beguile you, or ſeduce you,</hi> Coloſſ. 2. 17. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if ye be dead with Chriſt from the Rudiments of the world, whether Heatheniſh, or Jewiſh, Why are ye ſubject to Ordinances,</hi> ver. 18. <hi>which are nothing elſe, if not inſtituted by Chriſt, or if laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide by him, but human inventions,</hi> ver. 20. <hi>according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and doctrines of men,</hi> ver. 22. <hi>which are appointed, not by the Lord, but according to the pleaſure of men,</hi> as I think the Firſt day is, whereas the Seventh day is appointed by the Lord, and <hi>the Conſcience and whole life of man, ought to be governed by the commandments of God, without adding or diminiſhing,</hi> Deut. 12. 32. Matth. 15. 6, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which commandments of men, have indeed a ſhew of wiſdom in will-worſhip,</hi> Coloſſ. 2. 23. Worſhip which ſome men impoſed on themſelves and others, as if they could do and teach better and wiſer then God had commanded, which it ſeems is an old and humane Infirmity.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cawdrey,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Palmer,</hi> in their Treatiſe of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>pag.</hi> 50. ſay, <hi>That the Apoſtle in</hi> Col. 2. 16. <hi>ſpeaks of the other Holy days and Sabbaths, and not of the weekly Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sheppard</hi> in his Doctrine of the Sabbath, <hi>pag.</hi> 166. Theſ. 181. ſpeaking of <hi>Gal. 4. 10. Rom. 14. 4, 5. Col. 2. 16, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith, <hi>If we ſuppoſe that theſe places be meant of the weekly Sabbath, and riggidly urge them, we may quickly preſs Blood inſtead of Milk out of them, and wholly aboliſh (as</hi> Walleus) <hi>the Obſervation of any Chriſtian Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:48219:27"/>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Owen,</hi> in his Treatiſe of the Sabbath, <hi>pag.</hi> 214. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16, 17. ſaith, <hi>It is known, and confeſſed, that at that time all judaical Obſervations of Days, whether Feaſts, or Faſts, Weekly, Monthly, or Annual, were by themſelves and all others called their Sabbaths.</hi> And that kind of ſpeech was then in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe is here obſerved by our Apoſtles, <hi>it muſt therefore neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be allowed, that there were two ſorts of Sabbaths amongſt them, the firſt and Principal was the Weekly Sabbath, ſo called from the reſt of God upon the finiſhing of his Works, and that other day became from their Analogy, thereto to be called Sabbaths alſo.</hi> But that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between theſe Sabbaths was great, <hi>The one</hi> of them <hi>was ordained from the foundation of the world,</hi> before the entrance of Sin, and ſo <hi>belonged to all mankind in general</hi> (to all Mankind) the other were appointed in the Wilderneſs as a part of the peculiar Church-worſhip of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the one was directly commanded <hi>in the Decalogue,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>the Law of our creation</hi> (the Learned Doctor calls it the Law of our Creation) <hi>was revived and expreſſed,</hi> and that the other have their Inſtitution expreſly among the reſidue of ceremonial temporary Ordinances. See to the like purpoſe, <hi>p.</hi> 215, 216, 217.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Richard Byfield,</hi> in his Treatiſe on the Sabbath, <hi>p.</hi> 130. on <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. ſaith, <hi>That the Apoſtle there ſpeaketh not of the Fourth Commandment, becauſe he treateth expreſly of thoſe Sabbaths which were of the ſame rank with the New Moons.</hi> And that he ſpeaketh as he doth to the <hi>Galatians, chap. 4. 10. of the Obſervation of Days, Months, and Years, which pertained to the Servitude and Bondage of weak and beggarly Rudiments,</hi> as in <hi>ver. 9. Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that any precept of the Decalogue ſhould be ſo accounted, and reckoned as a weak and beggarly Rudiment, was far from the Apoſtle to think, and is abhorred to Chriſtian Ears, and Religion.</hi> Which I think Anſwer to the Doctor's Objections from <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which four Opinons I had from another hand ſince I came to <hi>London,</hi> and if I had the uſe of my own perſecuted Study, and other Books here, 'twere eaſie I think, to gather many more.</p>
            <p>And upon the whole, I find <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. to be againſt judging of Chriſtians then and there, and for ought appears againſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either way, and ſo this place, in whatſoever ſence we take it, makes only againſt judging in thoſe caſes.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48219:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 59. the Doctor takes the Law for the Seventh day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath to be a new Yoke to the Gentiles, becauſe it was given to the Jews as a Sign, or a diſtinctive mark, and for a perpetual Covenant, <hi>Exod. 31. 13, 16, 17. Ezek.</hi> 20. 12, 20. But this alſo will be againſt him, as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
            <p>That it was then new to the Heathens who obſerved Sunday I agree.</p>
            <p>Tis true, it was a ſign, but ſuch a ſign as all Proſelytes did em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and obey, till the coming of Chriſt, and <hi>by him is made a perpetual law,</hi> Matth. 5. 18, <hi>&amp;c. and ſo a perpetual ſign between him and his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho Circumciſion were a ſign, yet that is ceaſed, as before, and Baptiſm inſtituted.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Paſcal Lamb,</hi> tho it were a diſtinction between the <hi>Iſraelites, &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> yet being a Type of Chriſt, was lain aſide by him at his Inſtitution of the Lords Supper, as before by the words, <hi>This do in remembrance of me,</hi> Luke 22. 19. and ceaſed at his Death.</p>
            <p>And if it be meerly circumſtantial, and doth not at all influence Religion, whether in the Temple or other place God be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, <hi>John</hi> 4. 21. as the Doctor, <hi>p.</hi> 60. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 2. Yet God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo directly reſolved, that the Seventh day is the Sabbath, that is not a new Yoke, but an old Inſtitution, for the good of all Mankind, <hi>given at the Creation, and commanded in the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and ſo given by Chriſt.</hi> And with the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 18. and <hi>Luke 16. 17. made perpetual by him,</hi> and ſo I think is Chriſts Yoke, and an eaſie Yoke, (for it is only to take the commanded weekly Seventh inſtead of the Firſt day) <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 29, 30. which the Doctor and others ſhould willingly take upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 60. he adds, <hi>That the Jewiſh Sabbath</hi> (ſo he often calls it, and the Word Jewiſh runs much in his mind) <hi>ſeems to be, not a continuation of a former Sabbath, but rather a new Inſtitution</hi> (which I cannot find in the Word) as he ſays he has ſhewed before, which upon all the ſearch I have made I cannot find in all his Book; and I am loath to obſerve what I often read there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the great Latitude he takes that way.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:48219:28"/>
            <p>The Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 60. quotes the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 26. and ſays, <hi>I preſs and put great weight upon it, that the Seventh day is a Sign and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Covenant, to diſtinguiſh his People from other, that is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the People of the Jews from other Nations;</hi> which laſt words, <hi>the People of the Jews from other Nations,</hi> are added by the Doctor, whereas my words and meaning was, and is throughout, that the Sabbath was and is a perpetual Sign and Covenant with all true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that is, all true Believers of all Nations, in all Ages, from the beginning of the World to the end of it, to diſtinguiſh ſuch from the diſobedient to Gods Laws.</p>
            <p>And ſuch Artifice to add ſomewhat of his own to turn what is offered into his own Notion are blameable.</p>
            <p>And for the Doctor to ſay, as he there, <hi>That Circumciſion, the Paſſover, and the Seventh-day-Sabbath, were diſtinctive Marks, and at an end by the Death of Chriſt, is not ſo.</hi> 'Tis true of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion and the Paſſover that they are at an end, as before, but not of the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>So that a particular unravelling the many Allegations which I think are not ſo, would make this Reply too large.</p>
            <p>And he there makes the Sabbath aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>By which affirmings he may make other Commands aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if his Sayings and Comments may paſs for Doctrine, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh and overthrow any part of the Law of God.</p>
            <p>And adds there, <hi>That it is as meerly circumſtantial</hi> (as the place of Worſhip is) <hi>whether a Sabbath be kept on this or another day,</hi> which is the Doctor's Opinion, I think directly againſt <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. and againſt the Moral Law, <hi>Exod. 20. 9, 10, 11. Eſtabliſhed and made perpetual by Chriſt,</hi> Matth. 5. 17, 18. <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 17. beſides his indifferency to this or another day.</p>
            <p>My taking notice of the Doctor's Allegations about Facts which much concern this queſtion, may be excuſed, for that otherways ſome Readers may take them for true, and ſo be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their judging this Caſe, and many I have paſſed by, which obſerving Readers may note.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 61. he repeats from <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 13. that the Sabbath is a Sign, and yet <hi>p.</hi> 60. 61. doubts, was either not obſerved at all, or long before this time had been forgot.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:48219:28"/>
            <p>To which I Reply, if the Sabbath were a Sign, and ſuch a perpetual Sign, to be kept throughout their Generations, as it was (as the Doctor) and if it were a perpetual Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lord and them, as it was (as the Doctor) and made known to them as before, then ſurely they knew what day of the Week it was, and forgot it not, but obſerved it as they do, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where where they live to this day, which the Doctor has no reaſon that I know to doubt.</p>
            <p>And if that were ſo, that the Sabbath was long before forgot, and if the days of the Week are all uncertain, and none can tell which was which, Where are we then, but in utter uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties?</p>
            <p>And theſe Objections from the Seventh-day-Sabbath being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, and a perpetual Sign (and yet forgot and uncertain) contradict one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 61. he ſays, <hi>God had a particular reſpect to their Reſt from their Bondage in</hi> Aegypt, <hi>by the Preface to all the Commands,</hi> I the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of <hi>Aegypt, and by the cloſe of this Command, as repeated</hi> Deut. 5. 15.</p>
            <p>I Reply, be it ſo, yet that was ſuch a Deliverance, as the Gentiles then had a ſhare in, and as concerned all the People of God, at that time in the World, to take ſpecial notice of, and ſuch a Deliverance as is celebrated by all the Chriſtians in the World to this day, and doubtleſs will be ſo by all ſuch to the end of the World, and is celebrated as ſuch I think in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Common Prayer Book: See their Catechiſm.</p>
            <p>He there again recurs to <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. for a new <hi>Epocha</hi> of days, which is Replyed to before, that I find no ſuch thing there, as a new <hi>Epocha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>pag.</hi> 62. he ſays, <hi>As God by</hi> Moſes <hi>did give a new</hi> Epocha <hi>or Beginning to a Circulation of Sabbaths at</hi> Marah, <hi>ſo might Chriſt by himſelf, or his Apoſtles, fix another</hi> Epocha <hi>from his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Reply, that neither of theſe <hi>Epocha's</hi> being found in the Word, I think the Doctor blameable for ſaying God did give a new <hi>Epocha</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> which we do not read he did give, and if it be not in the Word, Why does the Doctor affirm, that God by <hi>Moſes</hi> gave it?</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:48219:29"/>
            <p>And he ſays, <hi>It is not expreſly ſaid that Chriſt did bid his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to fix another</hi> Epocha <hi>from his Reſurrection, yet he ſays he gave them Commandments for that purpoſe,</hi> Acts 1. 2, 3.</p>
            <p>Now for the Greateſt Man living to ſay, Chriſt gave them Commandments for that purpoſe, without a word from Chriſt for that purpoſe, ſeems to me highly blameable, <hi>Every word of God is pure, add thou not unto his words, leaſt he reprove thee,</hi> Prov. 30. 5, 6.</p>
            <p>We do ſuppoſe with Reaſon, the Commandments given by Chriſt to the Apoſtles were <hi>to preach the Goſpel, to diſciple all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to baptize in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, and to teach all things he had commanded them,</hi> Matth. 28. 19, 20. And ſee <hi>Mark 16. 15, 16, 17, 18. Luke</hi> 24. 46. to 52, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And we have other Commandments of Chriſt to ſome of his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 21. 1, 2. where he gave this to <hi>Peter</hi> (and in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> I think to all the reſt, and to all ſucceeding Miniſters of Chriſt) <hi>ver. 15. feed my Lambs,</hi> ver. 16, 17. <hi>feed my Sheep,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>follow me,</hi> which things did and do pertain to the Kingdom of God, of which things <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 3. Chriſt ſpake, but what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments in particular Chriſt gave to the Apoſtles for a new <hi>Epocha,</hi> does not appear that I know there, or elſewhere in the Word. But when they are produced, I hope his Miniſters and Churches will receive them, and what elſe the Apoſtles had by Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit, after Chriſts Aſcenſion, concern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the ordering of his Churchse, and rightly conſtituted Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or concerning any thing elſe which are recorded in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, we readily embrace.</p>
            <p>And I may requeſt the Doctor to take heed how he grafts any other Commandments for any purpoſe on Chriſt, but what are written in his Word, and if there be no ſuch Commandment, from Chriſt in the Word for that purpoſe, for his Apoſtles to fix ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Epocha</hi> from his Reſurrection; Why does the Doctor affirm it, if his Cauſe were good? yet ſuch means to defend it I think cannot be juſtified, and ſuch affirmations in Facts material to the main queſtion, I think ought to be reproved.</p>
            <p>As to what is ſaid <hi>p. 62. That not one jott or tittle of the law,</hi> meaning the Decalogue, <hi>is deſtroyed</hi> (I think he means that in <hi>Matth. 5. 17, 18.) but doth ſtill continue in force,</hi> and that we are all under that Law, as to the ſubſtance of the Duty.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:48219:29"/>
            <p>I Reply, that he there again acknowledges that we are all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Law, that is, under the Ten Commands, and that they ſtill continue in force.</p>
            <p>And if ſo, I would aſk the Doctor one Queſtion, who aſks me Divers.</p>
            <p>Who can reſolve us what is, and what is not Subſtance in Gods Commands, but God himſelf who gave them? he knows what bad work ſeveral have made by endeavouring to mangle them, eſpecially thoſe of the firſt Table, and indeed thoſe of both Tables.</p>
            <p>For what is ſaid <hi>p.</hi> 62. that <hi>Matth. 24. 20. Pray that your flight be not in winter, nor on the ſabbath day,</hi> which flight was about thirty eight Years after Chriſts Reſurrection, that that makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I think a fair anſwer to that is in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 73. 74 to which <hi>I</hi> add, that we cannot as well argue from hence, that it were a Sin to Labour in Winter, as on the Sabbath day, as the Doctor, <hi>p.</hi> 63. for that the Sabbath and Winter ſtand on diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Reaſons, which are obvious; the Sabbath was commanded, and the Winter bad to fly in becauſe of the Cold, Wet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and work was not forbidden in Winter, which was forbidden on the Sabbath, as the Doctor knows; and ſo <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 20. feems to the purpoſe, for the Sabbath was to continue by that Text, <hi>after the Death of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 63. my many other little Excurſions, as little to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he will not name, which is a ſhort way of anſwering.</p>
            <p>But ſays <hi>I</hi> take great pleaſure to expoſe the name of Sunday, by which name for diſtinction, <hi>I</hi> ſometimes call it, as himſelf does often, which (if he pleaſeth) he may henceforth call the Firſt day, its true name, as <hi>I</hi> often do, and other ſnubbing of Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day (as the Doctor there) <hi>I</hi> remember none, but he often calls the Lords Sabbath by a reflecting addition, which <hi>I</hi> often paſs by without ſnubbing again.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>'Tis true, ſome of the Heathens did Worſhip the Sun, but that they did it more on Sunday then on Monday, or Tueſday is more then he knows, or I can prove.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, Reply to which ſee <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 88, 89, 90. And for his, and others ſatisfaction herein, <hi>I</hi> refer them to Mr. <hi>Chafies</hi> Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tract on the Fourth Command, Reprinted 1692. which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing <hi>I</hi> think of uſe, being a Learned and Moderate Tract,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48219:30"/> tho I think Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> is out in the main Queſtion about the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, but helps much to prove the Worſhipping the Sun weekly upon Sundays, and many other Truths.</p>
            <p>In which Tract, Mr. <hi>Chafie, p. 20. chap.</hi> 9. does ſhew, that the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> (which ſeems to have been before <hi>Moſes,</hi> and one of the firſt Heatheniſh Dominions) and that all Nations Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Sun, with which Idolatry, he ſays, the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and many of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and generally other Nations were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, where <hi>p.</hi> 23. Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> tells us, <hi>That thoſe Sun-Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, on what Days of the Week they gave eſpecial Worſhip to the Sun or Moon, thoſe Days were called by the Names of the Day of the Sun, that is Sunday, and the Day of the Moon, that is Monday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So as Sunday is a very ancient day of the Week, and by him it appears they did very anciently divide their time by Weeks; which ancient weekly Sun-Worſhip, I think is proved by the Prohibition, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 19. See alſo <hi>Ezek. 8. 16. 2 Kings 23. 5. Deut. 17. 3, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which <hi>9th Chap.</hi> of Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s, we have alſo, how the Heathens always Worſhipped towards the Sun riſing, <hi>pag.</hi> 26. 27, 28, 29. which Authorities the Doctor may eaſily ſind.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> ſays, not any Nation of Note under Heaven, but adored the Sun as their God (the Sun was King, and the Moon was Queen, but the Sun was Trump). The <hi>Chaldeans, Perſians, Aegyptians, Phenecians, Trojans, Grecians, Romans, Scythians, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians, Tartars,</hi> &amp;c. all Worſhipped the Sun.</p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 71. Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> ſays, <hi>That Sunday was ſo called from our Heathen Anceſtors, who called this day</hi> (that is Sunday) <hi>ſo in honour of the Sun, whom they Worſhipped upon Sunday.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 30. Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> tells us, <hi>That to take off the Iſraelites from this Idolatry, the Lord uſed this means for one, that they ſhould not have the day of the Sun</hi> (that is, Sunday) <hi>for the day of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but the day before,</hi> (that is, the Seventh day) which I think refers to the time of the 16th or 20th of <hi>Exodus,</hi> which proves not only the Obſervation of the Seventh day by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but of Sunday by the Heathens, and that very anciently, and that continually in the weekly Circulation of Days, to this day, tho' I think Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> be out about the change of the Seventh day, as before and after.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:48219:30"/>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Chafie chap. 15. p.</hi> 59. gives the Teſtimony of divers Ancient and Learned Writers, which ſhew that the day of the Sun with the Gentiles was a Week-day, even the ſame which <hi>Mathematici,</hi> the Mathematicians (of old) called Sunday, which ſeem ſufficient Proofs, that the Sun was Worſhipped on Sunday, and that weekly, and that very anciently.</p>
            <p>Which <hi>9th.</hi> and <hi>15th.</hi> Chapters of Mr. <hi>Chafie,</hi> I think might give ſatisfaction, that all Nations of Note under Heaven Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Sun, and that very anciently, as far back at leaſt as the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that upon Sunday, and that towards Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing, that is, towards the Eaſt, and that weekly, whilſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Worſhipped weekly towards the Weſt, upon the Seventh day.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Chafie, p. 32. chap.</hi> 10. tells us, <hi>That the Holy Place, (or Holy of Holies) in the Temple at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>was towards the Weſt, and that when Worſhippers Prayed there, and Bowed, their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriors were towards the Sun-riſing, and their Faces Weſtward,</hi> and that Temple was built by the Lords ſpecial Direction.</p>
            <p>Which is one of the means (aſſigned by Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>) God uſed to take off the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from Worſhipping the Sun, ſo Sun-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was long before that.</p>
            <p>Which Tract of Mr. <hi>Chafie,</hi> I ſhall a little further conſider af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 65, 66, 67. the Doctor conſiders the Names of our Days, Sunday, Monday, Tueſday, Wedneſday, Thurſday, Friday, Saturday, which being now the known Names of the Days, he thinks we need no more ſcruple the uſe of theſe Names, then to talk of Pope <hi>Pious, Clement, &amp;c.</hi> Which I think he gives as anſwer to what is in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 90. againſt thoſe Names of Days, whoſe Original the Doctor agrees to be from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Idols.</p>
            <p>To which I Reply, from one of the Texts quoted in the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, Exod. 23. 13. Make no mention of the names of other Gods, neither let it be heard out of thy mouth,</hi> which Learned Mr. <hi>Chafie p. 30. l.</hi> 25. 26, 27. thinks refers to the Idol Names of the Days of the Week, which alſo proves the Antiquity of Sunday, and the Antiquity of Weeks. And the changing thoſe Names of Days I remember, was propounded by ſome of the Reformers, about the beginning of the Reformation in <hi>England:</hi> And Pope <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> the firſt of that Name, hating the Name and Memory
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48219:31"/> of the Gentile Gods, gave order that the Days ſhould be called by the Name of <hi>feriae,</hi> as I remember they are named in the Centuries.</p>
            <p>And it ſeems to me in this, and ſome other caſes, the main Doubt is, Whether we ſhall be ruled by the Word or no?</p>
            <p>And the Names of our Days of the Week being Idolatrous, as the Doctor agrees; I did in the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 90. upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Sunday, ſay a little about them, upon which the Doctor expatiates, and falls hard upon Scruples.</p>
            <p>Now cauſeleſs Scruples I yield are a Weakneſs, but a true Conſcientious Tenderneſs of Mind, not to offend God in any thing, wherein his Will in his Word is made known, is as I think, one of the moſt excellent Frames in Man. And if the Doctor under his Notion of Scruples, thinks to reflect upon Conſcientious Obedience to the Word, or any part thereof, (which I hope he does not) he will be much to blame, and God having ſo expreſly forbidden the mention of the Names of Idols, as theſe were by which the Days are called Sunſday, Moonſday, Tuiſcoſday, Wodenſday, Thorſday, Frizaſday, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnſday.</p>
            <p>And having alſo expreſly given us in his Word, the proper true Names of the firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, ſixth, and ſeventh Days, which Seventh day is called the Sabbath through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Scriptures, how ever that may ſeem to the Doctor, I make no Scruple to call the Days of the Week by the ſame Names as the Lord calls them; and if the Doctor will retain the old Idol Names without Scruple, notwithſtanding his own acknowledgement whence they are, and notwithſtanding the Word againſt them, I cannot help it, and it ſeems to me the moſt ſubtile of thoſe, who are ſo fond of holding faſt the Idol Names of Days, do doubt the conſequence of laying them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, as if it might by degrees introduce both true Names and Things.</p>
            <p>What is ſaid <hi>p.</hi> 68. 69, 70. (upon the occaſion of Scruples) about Spiritual Worſhip, and Worſhipping in Spirit and in Truth, I think does much concern all that fear God. But becauſe he does not ſpeak out directly, but only falls upon Scrupuloſities, and Shadows, and Circumſtances ſeemingly, though I think it pretty plain what he reflects upon, I ſhall reply but a little to that, and do refer the Reader to the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 32. where he may find in few words what I think from the ſecond Command (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48219:31"/> many other Scriptures) of Forms of Worſhip, Graven, Printed, or Written, and not inſtituted by the Lord, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
            <p>And in Reply to another, I think <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 2. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. about the Lords Prayer, that the ſame Cautions of, <hi>into thy Cloſet, ſhut thy Door, and in ſecret, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 6. do refer to, and explain <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 2. By which Cautions I think he ſhould be governed, and <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 32. he may ſee what I think from <hi>Eph. 5. 18, 19. Col.</hi> 3. 16. about ſinging; all which, and much more, ſome may count little things, Scruples, and cauſeleſs Scruples, nice Speculations, and needleſs Scrupuloſities, whereby (as ſuch may pretend) men are diverted from the Subſtantials of ſerious Religion, and ſpiritual Worſhip, which I think are very hard Reflections.</p>
            <p>Now I doubt, that not only the <hi>Romiſh</hi> World, but ſome others not of that way, as far as I can diſcern, are yet at ſome diſtance from their Duty in thoſe caſes, who are held to the Frames wherein they walk by the Authority of Men, and who for years paſt, have taken a liberty to comply with the Worſhip of the Country where they live, and take all down without chewing, as they find them, and ſo I doubt eſteem thoſe who differ from them (who upon the moſt diligent Search, and long Experiance, Worſhip God as they think, according to the Word) as ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and as ſtanding for little Circumſtances and Shadows, and ſo Conſcientious, Lively, Spiritual Worſhipping as but Shadows, and not ſubſtance of Chriſtian Worſhip, and ſuch Worſhippers, as diverters of others from ſerious Religion, many of whoſe Rods do yet bud and bloſſom, and bring forth Almonds, which if God ſo pleaſe, I ſhall be heartily glad to hear of their Rods who reflect upon them.</p>
            <p>Which little Circumſtances and Shadows as they are called, do not at all, as ſome pretend, influence the ſubſtance of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Worſhip, but are meer ſcruples, and minute things; and here it ſeems we have ſome thoughts of ſpiritual Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before of Preaching. And thus the very Life and Power of Chriſtian Worſhip is, as I think, reflected upon by ſome who have Frames of right Worſhip, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. and ſome of them correct Frames, that is, who have a way of Worſhip which has ſome ſimilitude, or likeneſs to right Worſhip) who change their Glory for that which doth not profit, and drink the Waters of other Rivers inſtead of Living Fountains, between which ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48219:32"/> Waters there is an internal difference, as great and manifeſt, as there is between good, wholeſome, running and living Springs, and dead Water, which may be ſome ſhort and weak Reply to the Reflections before mentioned.</p>
            <p>And if it were not to avoid offence, I had written, and might write more on this ſubject, which ſo much concerns all Mankind certainly, to know how to Worſhip Jehovah aright, and which for all Mankind, Miniſters and others, old and young, who have the Scriptures of the Old and New-Teſtament, and common Sence, and can ſpeak, and are by Grace made willing, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrably as eaſie to be put in practice without Crutches, and to be taught even to Children, without more adoe, as for ſuch to be taught, for juſt Reaſons, to ſpeak for any thing they ſtand in need of, and would deſire another, in whoſe power it is to give unto them.</p>
            <p>And upon this occaſion I had thought on ſome Lines about Swearing to a Point, and about abjuring Endeavours, whether lawful, peaceable, and honeſt Praying and Preaching Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours be excluded, but to avoid offence have croſſed them out.</p>
            <p>And to return: Tho it be all one to the Doctor, whether the days be called Saturday, Sunday, or <hi>Alpha, Beta, Gamma,</hi> in this we differ a little, he takes them as it ſeems, as he finds them in the World, and I take them as I find them in the Word, and I know no principle amongſt men, which does ſo effectually an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and cure all blamable ſcruples, and unquietneſſes of Mind, as a ſincere Obedience to all the Wills of God, which he that will do ſhall know, <hi>John</hi> 7. 17. which I doubt taking all as one, finds them, though it may lull in ſecurity, will never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
            <p>Pag. 66. He blames the whole of Judicial Aſtrology, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious, and only a Trick to amuſe credulous People, and make a gain of them, which is truly blameable, yet amongſt two ſorts of People is now very common.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:48219:32"/>
            <p>As to what is ſaid <hi>p.</hi> 68. about meeting once upon a Sabbath day, beſides Morning and Evening Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Reply, that I think that moſt for the real Service of God, and the Good of his People, which God has directed in his Word, which Rule, unleſs ſome neceſſity intervene, will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways found free from all Inconveniences; and for that I refer the Reader to the <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 83. 84. Almoſt all the Queſtions in theſe Papers depend much upon this, Whether Man ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be wiſer then God?</p>
            <p>Pag. 69. Whether to begin the Sabbath at Six or Twelve a Clock at Night? he thinks a thing not worth contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
            <p>And if it be ſo ſmall a thing, not worth contending about, Why does he not begin it when the Lord began it, that is in the Evening? one would think that none ſhould differ with the Lord over all for a ſmall thing, and of ſo little worth, when he has in his Word plainly told us his Will.</p>
            <p>And tho he thinks it not much more, whether on this, or that day, ſo the Sabbath be well kept, I do not yet know what he means by well keeping, but the words, this or that day, ſeem in him very indifferent to either, and I doubt will make any Man of that mind very cold in well keeping it.</p>
            <p>I think with the Doctor, we are to avoid fooliſh Queſtions, and to ſtudy things which make for true Peace, which Gods Word when it is obeyed, does moſt certainly do, and the fooliſh Queſtions are thoſe which croſs his Law and Word, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, and ſtriving againſt his Law and Word, is one of the worſt Fruits of the Fleſh, which Wars againſt his Will, and (to uſe ſome of his Words) <hi>in whomſoever that Temper is found</hi> (I doubt) <hi>it is for want of true Love, and other Fruits of the Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when ſome ſtudy to ſpin out Diſputes into ſo fine a Thread as to make the day begin and end at one time, which God has ſo firmly ſettled to begin and end at another, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5, 8, 13, 19, 23, 31. and to make the Week days all uncertain, which is which, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is to make that dark and difficult, which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and Works of God have made plain.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:48219:33"/>
            <p>I think within, we complain of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (and I think of others alſo) and deſervedly, for loading their Worſhip with Ceremonies, the number of which (beſides that they are meer humane Inventions, and ſo of no ſpiritual Uſe) are a burden which has broken down many eminently Holy and Learned in this Age, and which divert the Mind from Spiritual Worſhip.</p>
            <p>And I think it alſo ſomewhat of the ſame Miſchief, when Mens Minds are amuſed with uncertain dark Speculations, whereby they are endeavoured to be turned away from plain and eaſie Obedience, and Ground is layen for perpetual Doubts and Scruples, whilſt the Word ſays one thing, and ſome of great Learning and Influence do and teach another.</p>
            <p>And as to the Point in queſtion, I may ſay (as the Doctor <hi>p.</hi> 70.) <hi>I have upon the whole ſaid, as I weakly can, ſo much as I think may ſatisfie others, if they conſider it without Prejudice, a temper which the Holy Spirit can give his People, and I know when men have long eſpouſed a Notion by which they have a benefit, which Notion, if they let go, they looſe or endanger that benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no great wonder if they go on in their old way, till God does awaken them, but whether they go on with or without Doubts and Scruples, I know not.</p>
            <p>Nor do I know any thing can be ſo plainly ſaid, no, not from direct Word and Law of God, which by an Ingenious and Learned Man, may not be cavilled at, if he be ſo minded, and God will ſuffer him, and when the Lord has, as it ſeems to me, ſo plainly declared his Will, if ſome will not ſubmit to it, who elſe can help it?</p>
            <p>And when I have thus ſaid, I leave the Succeſs to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Pag. 71. he mentions a late Book on this Subject, to which I had drawn ſuch Anſwer as I then could, before I ſaw the Doctor's, but finding, as far as I remember, nothing therein in this caſe but what is offered with great Advantage by the Doctor, or what may be anſwered by obſerving Readers. I think to ſay but a little more to it.</p>
            <p>P. 5. of his Preface, he ſays, <hi>Suppoſe the Authors</hi> (he means the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Enquiry) Notion be Orthodox, and the contrary</hi> (that is, his own) <hi>Heterodox, he gives us the pernicious tendencies thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:48219:33"/>
            <p>That is, as I underſtand him, ſuppoſe it to be the mind of Chriſt, and a Sound and Orthodox Opinion, that the Seventh day is the true Chriſtian Sabbath (which is a fair, and I think a true Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition) yet he is againſt the Communicating of it as pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (which ſeems to me ſomewhat harſh) and ſuppoſe his own Opinion Erroneous and Heterodox; yet he is for it, and would not, as I underſtand him, have it contradicted: to which I only Reply, that I doubt the ancient Prophets, the Apoſtles, and the Reformers from <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. were not of that mind.</p>
            <p>In his little Book, he has theſe and other Reflections on the Author of the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> or on that he there offers, or on thoſe who receive it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Judaical, fanciful, baffled, abſurd, Heterodox, and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſcrupulous, ſuperſtitious, a Weed, and Thorn, rotten Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ſandy Foundations, falſe Meaſures, Proofs invalid, which it pitties him to ſee, uncharitable, rigorous, deluded Brain of ſilly Zealots, impertinency, empty, falſe Premiſes, ſilly Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, againſt all Reaſon and common Senſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſeem to me blameable.</p>
            <p>And he hopes <hi>p. 56. himſelf has written by Gods Aſſiſtance and Guidance,</hi> and <hi>p. 163. by Gods Aſſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>p. 116. by Gods Help.</hi> and (he hopes) <hi>his Guidance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Expreſſions I think may be uſed ſometimes, and in ſome Caſes, but men ſhould take heed how they uſe them, as if they were divinely inſpired, when they uſe them ſo interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>Pag. 70. to <hi>p.</hi> 79. the Doctor ſums up what he has offered, with all the advantages of a Learned Man, (as he ſometimes does before) with new words, on which I might make ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks.</p>
            <p>In that about the Fifth Command, <hi>p.</hi> 82. he tells us, <hi>His Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law, that is to determine who is to be reputed the Father,</hi> and this he applys, firſt to natural Parents, which as caſes may be put, may fall very heavy upon many Children, whoſe Parents were married, but not according to Human Law.</p>
            <p>And that General Rule from Humane Law, if I miſtake him not, he underſtands as determining the Law of God, for he ſays, <hi>p. 81. There be many things which the Word of God, or the Divine Law doth determine in</hi> Theſi (<hi>that is in a general Poſition</hi>) which <hi>when</hi> (in <hi>Hypotheſi) they come in practice,</hi> will require <hi>the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Prudentials, or Humane Laws,</hi> and he there, and <hi>p.</hi> 82.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48219:34"/> puts caſes upon the Eighth, Seventh, Sixth, and Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <p>So his General Rule is applyed to Laws in both Tables.</p>
            <p>And what he there ſays as to Natural Parents, the like he ſays as to other Superiours, as well as Natural Parents, and thoſe Laws which ſeem abſolute (ſays he) <hi>have yet their tacit Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons implyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Reply.</p>
            <p>That I think every Man ſhould beware how he ſets up Humane Laws, to determine againſt Gods Law in any caſe, for if Gods Law determine one thing to be a Duty or a Sin, and Mans Law determine the contrary, we are I think to obey God, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 19. whoſe Laws are Superiour to all Humane Laws.</p>
            <p>And he that in the Duties required in either Table, does al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the intervening, or coming in of Prudentials, or Humane Laws to controul or to determine the Word of God, or the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law, under that colour, or tacit Limitations implyed, and of room for Prudence to interpoſe, does, I doubt, unlord the Word and Law of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 7. 13. (which unlording the Word, or making it of no effect, <hi>Mark</hi> 7. 13. is alſo ſpoken by our Lord there, in the caſe of the Fifth Command, <hi>v.</hi> 9. to 13.) and does open a gap to enervate that Law of God.</p>
            <p>So that for any to ſay, that his Hunane Law that is to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine who is to be reputed my civil Parent, that is, who is my lawful Prince (whatever the Law of God determines in that caſe) under the ſubtile Words of <hi>Room,</hi> for Prudence to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and of tacit Limitations implyed, I doubt reſerves a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty inconſiſtent with the Word and Law of God, and very hard to be defended.</p>
            <p>For with thoſe Limitations, and if Humane Laws ſhall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Divine Laws; in ſome Parts of the World bad Men may find Pretences for the rankeſt Atheiſm, Theiſm, Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, and Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Spirit, notwithſtanding the Firſt Command, for the fouleſt Corruptions and Invaſions on Chriſtian inſtituted Spiritual Worſhip, notwithſtanding the Second, for the higheſt Prophanations of the Name of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, notwithſtanding the Third, as well as for pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sabbath, notwithſtanding the Fourth, and for Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Murder, Adultery, Stealing, Falſe-witneſſing, and Covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, notwithſtanding the other Six. And ſo it ſeems to me, ſuch
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48219:34"/> Limitations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have need of many Cautions to correct them.</p>
            <p>Now before I anſwer the Doctor's two Expedients, I firſt Reply to ſomewhat more I find in Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s Learned Tract.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 2. of his Epiſtle, ſays, <hi>That Chriſt the Son of God, hath taken away the Jews Sabbath, and Eſtabliſhed another, contrary to what God the Father inſtituted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now, tho I hope he was a very Good, as well as a Learned Man, yet he ſeems not to have then had clear Apprehenſions of Chriſt, as creating the World, and then reſting, nor of Chriſt, as inſtituting the Sabbath, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. nor of Chriſt confirming the Moral Law at <hi>Synai,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. nor of Chriſt making it perpetual, in <hi>Matth. 5. 18. Luke</hi> 16. 17.</p>
            <p>And in that Tract Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> ſpeaks of one Sabbath at the Creation, another in <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. and another at the Reſurrection of Chriſt; by which Notion he makes (to have been) three Sabbaths, from whom I think the Doctor takes up (if I miſtake him not) the like opinion of three Sabbaths, wherein I think they are both out, as before. And hereafter for Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s Notion of one Seventh-day-Sabbath at the Creation, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Seventh-day Sabbath in <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. I doubt would make two Seventh-day-Sabbaths in one Week of ſeven Days, which ſeems to me inconſiſtent, and would make the Firſt day more uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain alſo, beſides the uncertainties of the Doctor.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s opinion, <hi>p. 19, 20. That God hath not bound men to any ſet time to begin their Week;</hi> and <hi>chap. 8. p.</hi> 18. he ſays, <hi>The Law-giver himſelf hath plainly pointed out unto us in this Law,</hi> that is, <hi>in the Fourth Command, which is the Lords Day, or Sabbath of the Lord, and that is the day following the ſix days of Labour (with Men) and that in every nation, however they begin their Week, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venthday thereof is the Lords,</hi> p. 20. l. 9. p. 44. l. 6, 7. and his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>p. 7. l. 4. and that the Seventh day is not to be reckoned from the ſix days of God's Labour, but from the ſix days of Labour with Men;</hi> and ſo alſo in his Poſtſcript; but doth acknowledge <hi>chap. 11. p. 35. it hath been the general opinion, not only of the Vulgar, but of the Learned alſo (which opinion of the Learned I think is right)</hi> that the Seventh day commanded us in this Law, hath Relation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ſix Work-days of the Lord God, and not to the ſix Work-days with Men; which opinion of Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s for Mans Day, is, <hi>I</hi> think, contrary to <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2. for <hi>on the ſeventh day God
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48219:35"/> ended his work,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and reſted the ſeventh day from all his work<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo as twas the ſix days God wrought, which were the ſix Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-days, and the Seventh day God reſted, when he ended his Work, which was and is the Holy and Bleſſed Sabbath, which firſt appointment of the Lord I find no where changed, and ſo <hi>Exod. 20. 9, 10, 11. Six days ſhalt thou labour, but the ſeventh day is the ſabbath of the Lord, in it thou ſhalt not do any work,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For in ſix days the Lord made Heaven and Earth, and reſted the ſeventh day, wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſabbath day, and made it holy;</hi> and ſo it ſeems very plain, that the ſix, Working-days are thoſe on which the Lord wrought, and the Reſting, or Sabbath day, that which the Lord made Holy, and Bleſſed, and on which he Reſted.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> in <hi>chap.</hi> 12. ſays, <hi>God by his Law tyeth all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that at what time ſoever they begin the Week, they work not on the Seventh day, but ſanctifie it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which would be true if men began the Week as the Lord directed in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. but elſe by that Rule of Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s, Friday in <hi>Turkey</hi> (being their weekly Sabbath) the Chriſtians living in <hi>Turkey,</hi> are bound by the Fourth Command to ſanctifie Friday, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the ſixth Day of the Week, as the Lords Sabbath day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Turks</hi> there ſo do.</p>
            <p>And by the ſame Rule, thoſe Chriſtians who live in any Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Nation, where they Worſhip the Sun, and obſerve Sunday, there they muſt keep Sunday, and Sanctifie it, becauſe the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens where they live ſo do.</p>
            <p>And thoſe Chriſtians who live in thoſe Chriſtian Provinces, who keep the Seventh day, muſt keep the Seventh day as the Lords Day, becauſe others ſo keep it, and for that reaſon. And the like of thoſe who live in any part of the World amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe Chriſtians who live in thoſe Chriſtian Countries where they keep the Seventh-day-Sabbath, and the Firſt day al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, muſt keep I know not which of them by Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s Rule. And I take it as agreed, we are not to keep two Days in a Week, and that there are ſome ſuch people of theſe ſorts, ſee <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 119, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which Rule of Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi>'s, to reſolve which is the Sabbath day commanded by the Practice of the Country where we live, and that God hath not bound men when to begin their Week, is to ſet up Mans Day, as it ſeems to me, againſt the Lords
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48219:35"/> Day, and I think the Doctor writes by, for he ſeems to take it as he finds it.</p>
            <p>Which Rule I doubt will agree neither with the letter or mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. or of the Fourth Command.</p>
            <p>What Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> objects, <hi>That by the different Horizons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Paradice was</hi> (which <hi>p.</hi> 17. he ſays is unknown) <hi>no man can tell in the place where he liveth, when to begin the Day of Gods reſting at the Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, if our Sabbath did begin at the ſame inſtant of time that Gods firſt Reſt did, and Men were obliged to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, then that were an hard objection.</p>
            <p>But I know no place in the Word where it is ſaid, that every Sabbath afterward was to begin the ſame moment or time that the firſt Sabbath began in Paradice, or at <hi>Synai,</hi> &amp;c. Nor do I remember any thing ſo offered in any Writer. But that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath then did, and that Sabbaths afterward were to begin in the Evening everywhere, as Time was diſtributed into Days at the Creation, I think is before ſhewn, and that every Day of the Week began in the Evening, and laſted from Evening to Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that the Days began at or about Sun-ſet, and ſuppoſing the Darkneſs and light were the Evening and Morning of the three firſt Days, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5, 8, 13. ſure the Days then did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at mid-night, when Darkneſs began the Day, and Darkneſs and Light made up the Firſt day, and ſo the Second day, and ſo the Third day, which Word I think may ſettle that Point, that the Days did not begin at mid-night.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe alſo the Sun Created, as it was the Fourth day, and went round the Earth every day after it was created, as it did, and does to this Day. But on what part of the Fourth day the Sun was created is not certainly revealed that I know.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fowls and the Fiſhes were created upon the fifth day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> Adam <hi>was created on the Sixth day, and being created in the image of God, was made capable of knowing and contemplating the Perfections of him that created him, and of obſerving, and keeping Holy the Seventh day, which preſently after his Creation was Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, or made Holy, and Bleſſed, to let him into that Spiritual and Heavenly Life and Reſt, which his State of Innoceney made eaſie and pleaſant to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in Reply to one of the Doctor's Expedients, we may alſo ſuppoſe the Sun when ſet in the Firmament, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 17. travelled Weſtward round the Earth daily, as it ſtill doth.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:48219:36"/>
            <p>Now when the Sun did ſet the Fourth day, then the Fifth day began at Paradice, and when the Sun did ſet there next, the Sixth day began there, and when the Sun did next ſet there, the Seventh day began there, and that firſt Seventh day was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably as long as the other Days of the Week were, and are.</p>
            <p>And as the Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> (and ſo of <hi>Noah</hi>) travelled Eaſt, Weſt, North, or South, by degrees the Earth was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 19. and into whatever Country they came, as the Sun did ſet, ſo every Day of the Week began, and ſo on to this day.</p>
            <p>I Write as plain as I can.</p>
            <p>So as the weekly Seventh day did begin as the Sun did ſet, in every place round the Earth, from Paradice Weſtward, till the Sun came about in 24 hours to Paradice again.</p>
            <p>And for an inſtance, and for certainties ſake, <hi>I</hi> will begin with the Eleventh of <hi>March,</hi> the vernal <hi>Aequinox,</hi> 1692/3 which falls out to be the Seventh day of the Week.</p>
            <p>And the Seventh day at the Creation, did begin as the three Firſt days, and the other Week-days did, that is, in the Evening, as Mr. <hi>Chafie,</hi> and many other Learned Men do agree, at, or about Sun ſet, as I think is before ſhewn, and laſted 24 Hours, from Evening to Evening, according to <hi>Gen.</hi> 1, and <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>And the Sabbath day then was as it ſtill is, proportionably as long as the other Six Days of the Week allowed for Work, or rather wherein we are commanded to work, every of which ſix Days hath a Night or Darkneſs, as well as Day Light, in which Night or Darkneſs, if need be, Men may as lawfully work, as in the Day Light, tho generally the Day is made for Work, and the Night for Reſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Sabbath day hath an Evening, and a Morning, that is, a Night and Day of Holy Reſt, in which Night we may take Reſt, as in other Nights.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe who begin the Sabbath day in the Morning, they loſe the Evening, that is, the Night of that Day, which being no part of the Sixth day, nor (to ſuch) any part of the Seventh day, yet 12 Hours of time between the End of the Sixth, and Morning of their Seventh day, would ceaſe to them to be any part of the Week, if their Opinion would hold who begin the Sabbath in the Morning, unleſs they continue their Sabbath till the next Morning, and ſo turn God's firſt Inſtitution upſide down.</p>
            <p>Others who begin and end the Sabbath day at mid-night, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48219:36"/> then generally aſleep at both, when they begin and end it, they cannot tell when they begin or end it, and ſo muſt needs looſe thoſe Meditations which are peculiar to the one and to the other, and how any can begin or end it at mid night I know not.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing as before, the Evening in all Parts of the Earth, begins and ends the Day, then it is eaſie for all to know the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ending of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as the Evening and Morning made up every Day of the Week in Paradice, ſo Evening and Morning, as Mankind came about the Earth, made up every Day of the Week everywhere elſe, and as the Evening of the Seventh day came, ſo the Sabbath began, and the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ended everywhere as the reſt of the Days of the Week ended, that is, the Evening after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this be the true Scheme of Days, then ſomewhere in the Round of the Earth, every Inhabitant of it the <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1692/3. may not only keep the Sabbath, but certainly know when it begins and ends, and will have alſo their full ſix Nights and Days in the Week for their Work and Callings.</p>
            <p>And ſo as <hi>Adam</hi> or his Poſterity, and ſo as <hi>Noah</hi> or his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, travelled into any part of the Earth, Eaſt, Weſt, North, or South, where ever they came after ſix days of Travel, or other Labour, they might, as the Sun did ſet, Reſt the Seventh day.</p>
            <p>And all the tying up all parts of the Earth to the preciſe time or moment of the Lords reſting in the Evening of the firſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day at the Creation, and that the Seventh day Sabbath everywhere over the Earth, ever after, muſt begin and end the ſame minute the firſt Sabbath began and ended, whether it be at mid-day, or mid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>night, or any other part of Night or Day, ſeems a meer cramping of the Queſtion, without any Ground for it that I know from the Word.</p>
            <p>Whereas, if the days begin in the Evening, as I think they, do, and if the Evening and the Morning do conſtitute and make up a day as they do, then all the Scruples raiſed, when every Day of the Week, and in particular, when the Seventh day-Sabbath, all over the Earth, doth begin, and end, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that is, in the Evening, and ſo the two long days in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah</hi>'s and <hi>Ezekiah</hi>'s times, make no alteration of Days, as in the <hi>Enquiry.</hi> And ſo the Evening and the Morning make up e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Day of the Week to us in <hi>England,</hi> and to every other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48219:37"/> in the Earth, and for any other certain way to reſolve when the days do begin and end, but by Gods firſt appointment, I know not, for elſe it would put the moſt skilful Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans everywhere to a ſtand, when to begin and end the Days, and leave all Computations of Days, and Weeks, and Time in uncertainties and great diſorder.</p>
            <p>I take the <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> the vernal <hi>Aequinox,</hi> becauſe Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers agree the Sun to be then in the <hi>Aequator,</hi> as it is the <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> at the Autumnal <hi>Aequinox,</hi> at which times, the Days and Nights are by them ſaid to be equal all over the Earth.</p>
            <p>And if I had ſuppoſed the Sun in his Declination to either of the Topicks, the various Climates, and obliquity of the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> might have occaſioned diſputes, which, what I can, I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, and therefore take the <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1692/3.</p>
            <p>Nor do I enquire the place of Paradice, where it is, about which there are many diſputes, which place Learned Mr. <hi>Chafie</hi> confeſſeth is not known.</p>
            <p>And if we know not where Paradice is, then I cannot begin to give Inſtances of the Scheme before from thence, but if it lies Eaſt or Weſt from <hi>Mount Synai,</hi> that will make ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of time in the beginning and end of Days at <hi>Synai,</hi> and at Paradice, and yet not alter the days of the Week in either, for that the Seventh day of the Week in Paradice, was, is, and will be in the weekly Circulation of days, the Seventh day of the Week there.</p>
            <p>And the Seventh day in the Week at <hi>Synai,</hi> though it may differ in degrees of Longitude from Paradice, yet was, is, and will be in the weekly Circulation of Days, the Seventh day of the Week at <hi>Synai;</hi> and ſo of the reſt of the Days there and in every other place, as in <hi>Aegypt, Exod.</hi> 5. 5. where the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> kept the Sabbath, and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 1, 23, to 30. in the Wilderneſs of Sin.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding that difference in Degrees between Paradice and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and the Wilderneſs, and <hi>Synai,</hi> that made no difference between them, as to the beginning or ending of Days.</p>
            <p>In Paradice the Seventh day (as the Firſt, Second, and other Week-days) began in the Evening, and ended the next Evening, and ſo the Seventh day in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> in the Wilderneſs, and at <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> began in the Evening, and ended the next Evening. And
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48219:37"/> at all thoſe places, according to appointment at the making of the World, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. notwithſtanding the different Degrees or Minutes there might be of the Sun-ſetting at Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and at thoſe places.</p>
            <p>The Lord who knows all his own Works, the Beginning or Head of whoſe Word is Truth, <hi>Gen. 1. 1. Pſal. 119. 160. The entrance of whoſe words will give light, Pſal. 119. 130. Bleſſed and made holy the ſeventh day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sabbath,</hi> Gen. 2. 3. <hi>at Paradice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And bleſſed and made holy the ſeventh day at</hi> Synai, Exod. 20. 11, 12. although it is likely there are ſome Degrees or Minutes between.</p>
            <p>But how ever that be, yet we are pretty certain by the Maps where <hi>Synai</hi> was, and is, and where <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was and is.</p>
            <p>And according to the common received Principles of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, fifteen Degrees making an Hour, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſituate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix Degrees in Longitude, Weſtward from <hi>Synai,</hi> and ſo the Sun ſets at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> after his ſetting at <hi>Synai,</hi> twenty four Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of an Hour, or thereabout, that is, two fifth parts of an Hour, Weſtward from <hi>Synai,</hi> and yet that difference in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Seventh day at <hi>Synai,</hi> and of the Seventh day at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> made no alteration of the beginning or ending of the Seventh day-Sabbath at either.</p>
            <p>The ſame Seventh day which was commanded to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered to be kept Holy at <hi>Mount Synai,</hi> and which was repeated by <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> near <hi>Jordan,</hi> which place near <hi>Jordan</hi> may be about twenty two Minutes of Longitude from <hi>Synai,</hi> was certainly remembered and kept Holy by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> at <hi>Mount Zion</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with this difference, that the Seventh day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> twenty four Minutes of an Hour after it began at <hi>Synai,</hi> and ſome Minutes after it began near <hi>Jordan,</hi> which made no alteration of Days at either, but the Seventh day at <hi>Synai</hi> began in the Evening, twenty four Minutes of an Hour before it began at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Seventh day began twenty four Minutes of an Hour Weſtward, after it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at <hi>Synai,</hi> and yet was the Seventh day in both, and began in the Evening at both, that is, at or about Sun ſet at both, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the difference in time of twenty four Minutes, which may a little direct how to find when the Seventh day doth begin, and ſo of the reſt of the Days every where.</p>
            <p>This may be illuſtrated by further Inſtances, and for certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake, I will ſet out, and begin to reckon from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:48219:38"/> where they obſerved the true Seventh day Weſtward (without ſetting a Meridian there, altho it be Arbitrary, as the Doctor acknowledgeth, and may be ſet where we will) and by degrees bring the Account round the Earth to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> are about ſeven Degrees, that is, twenty eight Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Epheſus</hi> 9 Degrees, that is, 36 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Antioch,</hi> where <hi>Paul</hi> and his Company kept the Sabbath, <hi>Acts 13. 13, 14, 15, 16, 27, 42. q?.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Philippi,</hi> now ruined and deſolate, which was ſituated on the confines of <hi>Thrace,</hi> are about 14 Degrees, that is, 56 Minutes, where they kept the Sabbath, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Corinth,</hi> are about 17 Degrees, that is, 1 Hour and 8 Minutes, yet this difference of time, and ſo of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Sabbath, made no alteration of the Sabbath, where they alſo kept the Sabbath, <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 1, 4.</p>
            <p>As they did alſo as <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> Acts 17. 1, 2. where the Sun ſets about 1 Hour and 10 Minutes after it ſets at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And every where as the Sun did ſet, ſo the Sabbath day, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very other Day of the Week did begin and end as before.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Warſaw</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> are about 22 Degrees, that is, 1 Hour and 28 Minutes difference of Sun-ſetting.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Weſtward to <hi>Vienna,</hi> are about 29 Degrees, that is, 1 Hour 56 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> are about 30 Degrees, that is, 2 Hours.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> are about 40 Degrees (<hi>i. e.</hi>) 2 Hours and 40 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> are 44 Degrees, that is, 2 Hours 56 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> are about 48 Degres, that is, 3 Hours and 12 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 49 Degrees, that is, 3 H. 16 Min.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Dublin,</hi> about 53 Degrees, that is, 3 Hours and 32 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> are about 57 Degrees, that is, 3 Hours and 48 Minutes.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>New England,</hi> are about 120 Deg. that is, 8 H.</p>
            <p>I have paſſed over the firſt Meridian (which is Arbitrary as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and follow the Sun as it goes round the Globe of the Earth, till it comes about to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, which as to this way of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting, I think makes no alteration.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:48219:38"/>
            <p>And all theſe differences in Hours and Minutes, from the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Sun at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the ſetting of the Sun in all theſe before-mentioned, and all other places in the Earth, make no alteration of the Days, or of the Sabbath, all which begin every where, as the Sun ſets every where, and when the Sun every where did ſet, ſo the Sabbath day, as every other Day of the Week did begin and end as before.</p>
            <p>I ſtill follow the Sun from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Japan,</hi> the Sun may be ſaid to ſet ſeventeen Hours at <hi>Japan,</hi> after it ſets at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and when the Sun ſets at <hi>Japan,</hi> then the Seventh day begins at <hi>Japan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 11 of <hi>March,</hi> 1694/5.</p>
            <p>And from <hi>Japan</hi> (to paſs over the other Meridian and Reſt of the Land in <hi>Aſia</hi>) to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, about ſeven Hours.</p>
            <p>And ſo from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Sun goeth round the Earth to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, are 24 Hours, that is, from the Sun-ſetting at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the 11th of <hi>March,</hi> 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. to the Sun-ſetting at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> the 12th of <hi>March,</hi> 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. are 17 Hours from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Japan,</hi> and 7 Hours from <hi>Japan</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and 17 and 7 are 24 Hours, the Evening and the Morning which make up the Day.</p>
            <p>Which Scheme does, as I weakly can, travel round the World, and if it be right in the main, may anſwer ſome Doubts about the Days in this caſe. And if I miſtake, I think I do not wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtake, in which account I had no help from Globes, and ſo I have no great aſſurance, but that there may be miſtakes, and I am content to be corrected by the Learned Doctor, who excels in Aſtronomy, in Geography, and I think in moſt other Learning. Or any other Ingenious, Unprejudiced and Skilful, who may find miſtakes in the Degrees of Longitude, and in the Hours or Minutes, which however I think may not hurt the Opinion built upon it, that the difference in the time of the Sun ſetting in any of, and all thoſe places, and ſo of all other places in the Earth, the 11 of <hi>March,</hi> 1692/3. makes no alteration in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or ending of the Sabbath day, ſuppoſing as before, that day (with the reſt of the Days of the Week) did begin at the Creation, and does ſtill begin and end about the time of the Sun<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſetting, and ſuppoſe alſo that beginning and ending never alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince the Creation to this day.</p>
            <p>And if this be ſo, it ſeems demonſtrable, that every Day of the Week began every where in the Evening; and to the Seventh day alſo round the World as the Sun did ſet.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:48219:39"/>
            <p>The Doctor's other expedient, <hi>he would have me begin my Week on Monday, and then Sunday will be the Seventh day, I ſuppoſe he means if I can tell ſeven.</hi> But if the Doctor pleaſe to begin the Week as God begins it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 5. and if he reckon on <hi>v.</hi> 8. 13, 19, 23, 31, as God does, he will find <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. the Seventh day to be the Sabbath, and as it ſeems to me, to begin in the Evening.</p>
            <p>And in lieu of his two Expedients, I will with his Favour, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him and others two things,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1st.</hi> Upon the Fourth Command, <hi>Exod. 20. 8, 9. To take heed how they aſſume a liberty to alter any Command of God, or any jot or tittle thereof, becauſe of</hi> Mat. 5. 18, 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> Rev. 22. 18, 19, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Upon the Second Command: <hi>Whatever be the manner of Worſhip in the place where he or they live, unleſs they be ſure that for Matter and Manner it be according to Chriſts Inſtitutions: That they beware how they take it as they there find it, which though it may be a probable means of worldly Advantages, yet I have ſome doubt, it is no ſound Rule to Worſhip by, becauſe the Lord thy God is a jealous God, viſiting iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhewing mercy to thoſe who love him, and keep his commandments,</hi> Exod. 20. 4, 5, 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> Deut. 5. 8, 9, 10, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And upon the whole, I think not A, but the Seventh-day-Sabbath was obſerved by the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 2, 3. and afterward by the Patriarchs, by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and by the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and in the Wilderneſs of Sin, where they had <hi>Mannah,</hi> and at <hi>Mount Synai,</hi> and at <hi>Mount Zion</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and to the end of the Old Teſtament, <hi>to whom the Lord made known his ſabbath,</hi> Neh. 9. 13, 14. his Sabbaths as before, <hi>and to whom he gave them as a ſign, and as an everlaſting covenant, and that not A, but, The Sabbath was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved perfectly and conſtantly by Chriſt during his life,</hi> which I think proves it not forgotten, nor altered to his time, and that not A, but The Sabbath was obſerved by his Diſciples, inſpired by the Holy Spirit after his Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, which alſo proves it not forgotten, nor altered then.</p>
            <p>And as their loſing the Knowledge, which was the Seventh day, is not in the Word that I know, ſo the certain Seventh day, was preſerved by all Nations, Worſhipping the Sun on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, Mr. <hi>Chafie, p.</hi> 20, &amp;c. <hi>and all the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>before Chriſt, and all the</hi> Jews <hi>ſince (that we can read or hear of) and ſome Chriſtians ſtill keep not A, but The Seventh day, and many Chriſtians keep the firſt day, other Chriſtians keep both Seventh and Firſt day,</hi> as in the <hi>Enquiry;</hi> and the early and long Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies about what Days to keep the Paſſover on, and the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Counſels, Centuries, and our own Records, Ancient and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48219:39"/> Modern, as in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> ſeem plainly to prove, that the Seventh day was never altered, from Chriſts time to this day, nor from the Creation to Chriſts time, and that the Seventh day in <hi>England</hi> is the ſame Seventh day varying the Hours and Minutes as before, which was obſerved by Chriſt, which was made perpetual by Chriſt, which was obſerved at <hi>Mount Zion,</hi> which was given at <hi>Synai,</hi> and <hi>which was bleſt and made holy at the Creation,</hi> Gen. 2.</p>
            <p>And here I might alſo obſerve, that the Doctor neither denys nor anſwers the Authorities in the <hi>Enquiry,</hi> for obſerving the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, 400 and 700 years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> after Chriſt, and for the changing the Seventh day to the Firſt day by <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. not the clear Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the firſt bringing in the Firſt day into <hi>Scotland,</hi> by a Counſel there above 1200 years after Chriſt, nor that of the King and Nobles of <hi>England</hi> here to like purpoſe, <hi>Enquiry p.</hi> 106. to 114, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor that how all our Antient and Modern Records in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to this day, call the Seventh day of the Week the Sabbath day, <hi>Enquiry, p.</hi> 117. to which the Doctor ſays nothing, nor to that of the many Provinces and one Empire ſtill obſerving the Seventh day, <hi>Enq. p.</hi> 119. 120. And all put together, I think may ſufficiently diſprove the uncertainty which is the Seventh day, which the Doctor ſo often would leave doubtful againſt himſelf, and may prove that our Seventh day of the Week is the true Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, <hi>bleſſed and made holy at the creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I inſiſt, that Chriſts Command to keep Holy the Seventh day, not being altered, nor repealed, but with all the reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and made perpetual by him, ſtill binds, as all the reſt of the Commands do.</p>
            <p>I have paſſed by divers Expreſſions in the Doctor's Book, but have not that I know declined any thing that required, as I think, further Reply, and what he objects again, and again I often think it enough to anſwer to but once. And if I do not fully repeat his Objections or Words at large, it is to make this Reply as ſhort as I can, and the Reader may reſort to the Book.</p>
            <p>And to conclude: Inſtead of further ſumming up what I have weakly written here in Reply to the Learned Doctor and others, as I could, I commend to the Reader a few Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Gen. 2. 2, 3, 4. <hi>On the ſeventh day God ended his work which he had made, and he reſted the ſeventh day from all his work which he had made, and God bleſſed the ſeventh day, and made it holy, becauſe that in it he had reſted from all his work which he had created and made,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:48219:40"/> and ſo the Sabbath is the day upon which God reſted after his Work, and which he Bleſſed and made Holy, who is, <hi>v. 4. Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah Aelohim,</hi> the Lord God, ſo the Seventh day is the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Exod. 16. 29. <hi>The ſeventh-day-ſabbath is ſaid to be as it is, a gift, The Lord hath given you the ſabbath,</hi> and ſo we ſhould take it as a Gift from him, as his Gift, and as the Lords day</p>
            <p>Exod. 20. 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Remember the ſabbath day to keep it holy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The ſeventh day is the ſabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> and ſo the Seventh day is the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Exod. 31. 13. The Lord calls them <hi>my ſabbaths, verily, my ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths ye ſhall keep,</hi> ſo the Sabbath is the Lords day, <hi>it is a ſign between me and you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that ye may know that I am the Lord that doth ſanctifie you,</hi> v. 14. <hi>and ye ſhall keep the ſabbath becauſe it is holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to you,</hi> v. 15. <hi>Six days work ſhall be done, but the ſeventh is the ſabbath of reſt, holineſs to the Lord,</hi> v. 16. <hi>the ſabbath, a perpetual co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, tis holineſs to you,</hi> v. 14. <hi>and holy to the Lord,</hi> v. 15. &amp; v. 16. <hi>the ſabbath, a perpetual covenant,</hi> and v. 17 <hi>a ſign for ever. For in ſix days the Lord made heaven and earth, and on the ſeventh day he reſted, and was refreſhed,</hi> ſo the Seventh day is the Lords day. And <hi>v. 18. The Lord gave to</hi> Moſes <hi>to tables of teſtimony, written with the finger of God.</hi> And <hi>Exod. 32. 15, 16. the tables were the work of God, and the writing the writing of God, upon which tables of teſtimony or witneſs the fourth command was one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Exod. 35. 2. <hi>Six days ſhall work be done, and on the ſeventh day it ſhall be to you holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lev. 23. 3. <hi>Six days ſhall work be done, but the ſeventh day is the ſabbath of reſt, an holy convocation, ye ſhall do no work therein, it is the ſabbath of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. ſo the Seventh day is the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Lev. 23. 32. <hi>from even unto even ſhall ye celebrate your ſabbath,</hi> which I think is directing in an Humiliation day, which is there to begin in the Evening when they were to afflict themſelves.</p>
            <p>And I think ſtates this part of the Queſtion, when the Days began, that is, in the Evening, and when they ended, that is, at the next Evening, which the Dr. <hi>p.</hi> 27. thinks, began and ended at mid-night.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Numb.</hi> 15. 32. we have the caſe of the Man who gathered ſticks not A, but The Sabbath day, which is a great, certain, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable example againſt the leaſt prophaning of the Sabbath day.</p>
            <p>Deut. 5. 12. <hi>Keep the ſabbath day to ſanctifie it, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee, 13. Six days labour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v. 14. But the ſeventh day is the ſabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c. ſo the Seventh
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48219:40"/> day is the Lords day of Reſt (<hi>i. e.) the ſeventh day is the Lords day,</hi> Pſal. 119. 1, 6. <hi>bleſſed are thoſe who walk in his law, and in keeping of his commandments there is great reward,</hi> Pſal. 19. 11.</p>
            <p>Eſai. 56. 2. <hi>Bleſſed is the man who keepeth the ſabbath from pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting it,</hi> v. 4. 6. <hi>from polluting it,</hi> Ezek. 20. 13, 16, 24 <hi>my ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath they greatly polluted,</hi> if we would be Bleſſed, keep his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and dont pollute them, which it ſeems was <hi>Iſraels</hi> Sin, of old.</p>
            <p>Eſai. 58. 13. <hi>If thou turn away thy foot from the ſabbath, from doing thy pleaſure on my holy day, and call the ſabbath a delight, or delights, the holy of the Lord</hi> (ſo the Sabbath day is the Lords day) <hi>honourable, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking thine own words,</hi> v. 14. <hi>then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. and is not that a deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble frame?</p>
            <p>Ezek. 22. 1, 2. <hi>The word of the Lord, thou haſt prophaned my ſabbath,</hi> v. 26. <hi>her Prieſts have violated my law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and have hid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their eyes from my ſabbaths.</hi> So the Sabbath day is the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Ezek. 44. 4, 5, 15, 24. <hi>in the propheſie of the new temple there is a promiſe, that the Prieſts who ſhall come near unto the Lord to miniſter unto him, they ſhall hallow my ſabbaths.</hi> So the Sabbath day is the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Matth. 5. 17. <hi>Think not that I am come to deſtroy the law,</hi> v. 18. <hi>For verity I ſay unto you, till heaven and earth paſs, one jot, or one tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhall in no wiſe paſs from the law, till all be fulfilled,</hi> dont think that Chriſt altered one tittle of the Law, and ſo not one jot or tittle is yet paſſed from the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 8. Chriſt is ſaid to be Lord of the Sabbath day, and if Chriſt be Lord of the Sabbath day, then the Sabbath day is the Lords day.</p>
            <p>Mat. 24. 20. <hi>Pray that your flight be not on the ſabbath day,</hi> which flight was about 38 years after Chriſts Death, which I think ſhews it was to continue after his Death, that is, as I think, as long as the World laſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 18, 19, 20. Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>go teach all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have commanded you, and Chriſt with the Father and holy Spirit, one Jehovah, gave the commands as before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mark</hi> 1. 21. after Chriſts Baptiſm by <hi>John,</hi> v. 9. <hi>Jeſus came into</hi> Galilee, <hi>preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom of God,</hi> v. 14. <hi>repent ye, and believe the Goſpel,</hi> v. 15. <hi>then he calls</hi> Simon, <hi>and</hi> Andrew,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48219:41"/> James <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>and they followed him,</hi> v. 16 to 20. <hi>and they went into</hi> Capernaum, <hi>and ſtraitway, on the ſabbath day, he entered into the Synagogue, and taught,</hi> and <hi>Mark 2. 27. the ſabbath was made for man, for his good, for his ſpiritual good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark 16. 1, 2. <hi>Jeſus came into his own country and his diſciples follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and when the ſabbath day was come, he began to preach in the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue,</hi> which alſo proves the Sab. made for the ſpiritual uſe of man.</p>
            <p>Luke 4. 16, to 27. in <hi>v.</hi> 14. (after his being tempted, <hi>v. 13.) Jeſus returned in the power of the ſpirit, into</hi> Galilee, and <hi>v. 15. taught in their Synagogues,</hi> and <hi>v, 16. he came to</hi> Nazareth, <hi>where he had been brought up, and as his cuſtom was, he went into the Synagogue on the ſabbath day, and ſtood up for to read, and preached the Goſpel,</hi> v. 17, to 29. <hi>and then he came down to</hi> Capernaum, <hi>and taught them on the ſabbath day,</hi> beſides divers other places in the Evangeliſts, which do all prove the Sabbath made for the ſpiritual good of Man. And ſo I think we have enough to prove that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt kept the Sabbath during his life, and that perfectly; <hi>for he was a lamb without ſpot or blemiſh,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 19, &amp;c. and that the Seventh day Sabbath was made holy for the ſpiritual Good of Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 17. it is eaſier for Heaven and Earth to paſs, then one tittle of the Law to fail, which one would think are ſtrong words, and of Authority in this caſe. And Heaven and Earth are not yet paſſed, and ſo not one tittle of the Law does yet fail; and if this Scripture be true, as it ſurely is, it mightily proves the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day to be the Sabbath, <hi>Ezod.</hi> 20. 10. which Seventh day in the Fourth Command is more then a tittle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 54, 55, 56. And when he was Crucified, Dead and Buried, and the Sabbath drew on, the Women followed after, and beheld the Sepulchre, and how his Body was laid, and they returned and prepared Spices and Ointments, and reſted, not A, but The Sabbath day, according to the Commandment, that is, according to the Fourth Commandment, and ſo the Seventh day was not altered then, and ſo kept not A, but the Sabbath day, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts Death and Burial, as in probability all other Believers then did, for I do not remember to have read of any that deny it.</p>
            <p>John 14 15. <hi>If ye love me keep my commandments,</hi> Exod. 20. 6. Deut. 7. 9 John 14. 21. <hi>he that hath my commandments and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me, 23. If a man love me he will keep my words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>John 15. 10. <hi>If ye keep my commandments ye ſhall abide in my love, 14. ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</hi> Are we Friends of Chriſt, and would we abide in his Love, then keep his Commands.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:48219:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts 13. 13, 14. Paul</hi> and his Company went into the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue at <hi>Antioch,</hi> on the Sabbath day, and <hi>v. 15. After the reading of the law and the prophets,</hi> v. 16. Paul <hi>ſtood up and preached Chriſt to them, from</hi> v. 16. to 41. and, <hi>v.</hi> 42. the Gentiles beſought that theſe words might be preached to them the next Sabbath, not the next Morning upon the Firſt day of the Week, but the next Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and ſo after the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt, and after the Diſciples were all filled with the Holy Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 1, 4. Tis certain <hi>Paul</hi> kept the Sabbath, and Preached to Jews and Gentiles, not upon the Firſt day of the Week, but upon the Sabbath day.</p>
            <p>And we have the like <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 44. the next Sabbath day (not the next Morning) almoſt the whole City came together to hear the Word of God, and <hi>v. 47, 48. as many of the gentiles as were ordained to eternal life believed:</hi> ſo divers Gentiles were here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto Chriſt on the Sabbath day, <hi>v. 49. the word of the Lord was publiſhed throughout all the region,</hi> and <hi>v. 52. the diſciples were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with joy, and with the holy ſpirit,</hi> and is not this a deſirable frame? and doe not all theſe prove that the Sabbath was made for the ſpiritual good of Man?</p>
            <p>And <hi>Acts</hi> 14, 1. In <hi>Iconium, Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> went both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Synagogue of the Jews, and ſo ſpake, that a great multitude both of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>Greeks</hi> believed, <hi>a great multitude,</hi> and <hi>v. 3. The Lord gave teſtimony to the word of his grace, by ſigns and wonders done by them. Acts</hi> 16. 1, 3, 12, 13, 14, 15. at <hi>Philippi, Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> on the Sabbath day went out of the City by a Rivers ſide, where Prayer was wont to be made, and ſpake to the women which reſorted thither, where <hi>Lydia</hi> was converted, whoſe heart the Lord opened, that ſhe attended unto the things which were ſpoken of <hi>Paul,</hi> and was baptized, and her Houſhold; which Scriptures with many others, do ſhew, and I think prove that the Sabbath was not altered, but did continue after Chriſts Aſcenſion, and was obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 1. to 4. at <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> where was a Synagogue of the Jews, Paul, as his manner was (as Chriſts manner was <hi>Luke 4. 16.) went in unto them, and three ſabbath days reaſoned with them out of the ſcriptures,</hi> alledging, that Chriſt muſt needs have ſuffered, and riſen again from the Dead, and that this Jeſus whom he preach'd unto them is Chriſt, and ſome of them believed; and conſorted with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and of the devout Greeks, that is of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, a great multitude, and of the the chief Women, not a few
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48219:42"/> were converted to Chriſt upon the Sabbath day, ſo the Law for keeping Holy the Sabbath, was not then paſſed away.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 1, 2, 4, 5, 19. at <hi>Corinth Paul</hi> Reaſoned, that is (<hi>Greek</hi>) Preached in the Synagogue every Sabbath, and perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Jews and the Greeks, that is, the Jews and Gentiles. And what greater, and ſtronger, and clearer Evidence and Proof for the Seventh-day-Sabbath can Man deſire, then theſe plain Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are? and that it was at firſt Inſtituted, Bleſſed, and made Holy, and throughout the Scriptures of Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, uſed for the converſion and eternal good of Man.</p>
            <p>Rom. 3. 31. <hi>Do we then make void the law through Faith, be it not, yea, we eſtabliſh the law.</hi> Rom. 7. 12. <hi>The law is holy, and juſt, and good.</hi> Rom. 7. 14. <hi>we know that the Law is Spiritual.</hi> Rom. 10. 4. <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs, to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth.</hi> And 1 Cor. 9. 21. Paul <hi>was under the law to Chriſt,</hi> and 1 Cor. 11. 1. he ſaith, <hi>be ye followers of me, even as I alſo am of Chriſt, who</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 3. <hi>dyed for our ſins,</hi> and 1 John 3. 4. <hi>ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the law, but</hi> Gal. 3. 11. <hi>no man is juſtified by the law,</hi> v. 13. <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law,</hi> v. 21. <hi>Is the law againſt the promiſes of God, God forbid, or be it not,</hi> v. 24. <hi>but our ſchoolmaſter unto Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by faith, who</hi> Tit. 2. 14. <hi>gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all anomy, or contrariety</hi> (in Opinion or Converſation) <hi>to the law of God,</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10. the Lord ſaith, <hi>I will put my laws into their minds, and write them in or upon their hearts,</hi> which ſurely is greatly deſirable, that his Law be written on our Hearts. And we have the like promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 15, 16, 17. ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will put my laws into their hearts, and in their minds will I write them,</hi> which Law in <hi>Jam.</hi> 20. 8. is called a Royal Law, that is, the Kingly, Chief, and univerſal Law, under which all other Laws of God are comprehended, which Chriſt, the Lord and King over all, hath preſcribed and commanded, 1 <hi>John 1. 10. If we ſay that we have not ſinned, we make him a liar,</hi> 1 John 2. 3. <hi>and hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his commandments,</hi> v. 4. <hi>he that ſaith I know him, and keepeth not his commandments (is miſtaken</hi>) v. 6. <hi>he that ſaith he abideth in him, ought himſelf ſo to walk, even as he walked, and Chriſt kept the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> and 1 John 3. 22. <hi>whatſoever we ask, we receive of him, becauſe we keep his commandments,</hi> and 1 John 5. 3. <hi>for this is the love of God, that we keep his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, 2 Ep.</hi> of Joh 6. <hi>this is love, that we walk after his commandments,</hi> Rev. 12. 17. The Dragon was wroth, and went to make War with thoſe who kept the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and have the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, and <hi>Rev. 14. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Here are thoſe who keep the commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus,</hi> and Rev. 22. 14. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his commandments, that they may have right to the tree of life, and may enter through the gates into the city.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:48219:42"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 28. <hi>for Cronologies,</hi> read <hi>Cronologers,</hi> p. 4. l. 5. r. <hi>one,</hi> p. 5. l. 15. for <hi>v.</hi> 19. r. <hi>v.</hi> 16. p. 5. l. 39. r. <hi>but,</hi> p. 9. l 27. <hi>dele and,</hi> p. 10. l. 15. <hi>for</hi> Jaſhebeth, r. Laſhebeth, p. 12. l. 15. <hi>for</hi> Morah, r. Marah, p. 13. l. 14. <hi>dele</hi> 22. l. 15. <hi>for</hi> Exod. 12. 12, 13. r. Exod. 12. 32. p. 15. l. 4. <hi>for</hi> 23. r. 2, 3. p. 16. l, 28. <hi>for</hi> 15. r. 14. p. 18. l. 37. <hi>dele</hi> 14. p. 19. l. 26. <hi>for v.</hi> 5. r. <hi>v.</hi> 6. p. 21. l. 1. <hi>dele</hi> &amp; 42. p. 23. l. 18. <hi>for</hi> 6. r. 16. l. 21. <hi>dele</hi> &amp; 21. 46. p. 24. l. 23. <hi>for one,</hi> r. <hi>One,</hi> p. 29. l. 40. <hi>for</hi> Num. 6. r. Num. 9. p. 33. l. 5. <hi>for</hi> 30. r. 13. l. 35. <hi>for</hi> 30. r. 13. p. 34. l. 18. <hi>dele it,</hi> p. 41. l. 23. <hi>for ſacrificis,</hi> r. <hi>and ſacrifices,</hi> p. 46. l. 6. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, l. 7. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 47. l. 6. <hi>for</hi> 15. r. 5. <hi>and for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, l. 8. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, l. 9. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, l. 17. <hi>for muſt be, one,</hi> r. <hi>muſt be, are,</hi> p. 49. l. 32. <hi>dele and,</hi> p. 50. l. 6. <hi>for Apoſtles,</hi> r. <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> l. 9. <hi>for day,</hi> r. <hi>days,</hi> l. 14. <hi>for other,</hi> r. <hi>others,</hi> p. 53. l. 11. <hi>for was,</hi> r. <hi>is,</hi> p. 54. l. 34. <hi>for? put<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> p. 58. l. 21. <hi>for Anp,</hi> r. <hi>And,</hi> l. 26. <hi>dele as,</hi> p. 63. l. 31. <hi>for His</hi> r. '<hi>Tis,</hi> p. 64. l. 17. <hi>for or,</hi> r. <hi>of.</hi> l. 23. <hi>for his,</hi> r. '<hi>tis,</hi> p. 65. l. 20. r. <hi>as before and hereafter,</hi> p. 72. l. 30. r. <hi>degrees.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
